<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A discourse deliver'd in two sermons preached in the cathedral at Ely, in September 1684, not long after the death of the Right Reverend Father in God Peter Gunning, late Lord Bishop of Ely / by Humfrey Govver ...</title>
            <author>Gower, Humphrey, 1638-1711.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1685</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 128 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A41725</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1458</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18728</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12662086</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12662086</idno>
            <idno type="VID">65451</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A41725)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 65451)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 355:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A discourse deliver'd in two sermons preached in the cathedral at Ely, in September 1684, not long after the death of the Right Reverend Father in God Peter Gunning, late Lord Bishop of Ely / by Humfrey Govver ...</title>
                  <author>Gower, Humphrey, 1638-1711.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[7], 66 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by John Hayes ... for John Creed ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Cambridge :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1685.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Gunning, Peter, 1614-1684.</term>
               <term>Church of England --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:65451:1"/>
            <p>A
DISCOURSE
Deliver'd in
Two Sermons,
PREACHED in the
Cathedral at ELY,
in <hi>September</hi> 1684.</p>
            <p>Not long after the Death of the
RIGHT REVEREND FATHER in <hi>GOD</hi>
PETER GUNNING
Late <hi>Lord Biſhop of</hi> ELY.</p>
            <p>By HUMFREY GOVVER D. D. Maſter of <hi>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> John's
College</hi> in <hi>Cambridge</hi> and one of the Prebendaries of <hi>ELY.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>CAMBRIDGE,</hi>
Printed by <hi>John Hayes,</hi> Printer to the Univerſity. For <hi>John Creed,</hi>
Bookſeller there. 1685.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:65451:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:65451:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Right Reverend Father in God
FRANCIS Lord Biſhop of ELY
and Almoner to His MAJESTY.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is now near five moneths ſince
this Diſcourſe was deliver'd in Two
Sermons in your Lordſhips <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral</hi>
Church at <hi>ELY.</hi> So
long have I been able to keep it confin'd to
that privacy, for which it was intended,
notwithſtanding many endeavours that were
uſed to make it Publick. I had no reaſon
to be eaſily perſwaded to offer to the world
any thing ſo mean on ſo Great a Subject.
That, which might ſerve well enough from the
<hi>Pulpit</hi> to expreſs my own Duty and Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence
to the Bleſſed Memory of this Holy
Prelate, and could raiſe ſuitable Affections in
that one Auditory for which theſe Sermons were
<pb facs="tcp:65451:3"/>
compos'd, will not, perhaps, deſerve Pardon
coming from the <hi>Preſs</hi> and preſented to the
Publick view. It may be expected from a
Diſcourſe of this nature, that carries in its
Title Page the Great Name of <hi>Biſhop
GUNNING,</hi> that it ſhould bear ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion
to the Excellent Subject, adorn the
Great and Good Mans memory and render
Him Lovely and Admirable in the Lively
expreſſion of His <hi>Character,</hi> as He really
was in the Perfections of His <hi>Soul</hi> and the
whole Tenour of His <hi>Life.</hi> But that's an
undertaking far above My reach and beyond
the Power of any words that I know. If ſo
Happy a Performance may be reaſonably expected
from any Pen, My Lord, it muſt be Yours; You
beſt underſtand and can beſt Expreſs what an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable
Treaſure the World lately Enjoyed, and
now Laments as loſt, in Your Renowned Predeceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſour.
But, if the Important Affairs that take
up your time and the many Duties of that High
Station, in which God and the King have ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily
plac'd You, will not allow Your Lordſhip
leiſure to oblige our Age and Poſterity in this par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,
<pb facs="tcp:65451:3"/>
I hope ſome other will be found ready,
and, in ſome good Degree, qualified for ſuch an
undertaking.</p>
            <p>In the mean time I have ſuffer'd my ſelf to be
overrul'd by my Friends, but eſpecially Your
Lordſhip, whoſe Commands I do not uſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute;
but ſtill delight to Obſerve and Obey the
leaſt intimations of Your Pleaſure, as well now
that You are <hi>Biſhop</hi> of the <hi>Dioceſs</hi> as when
You were <hi>Maſter</hi> of the <hi>College.</hi> But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
made Me yeild more patiently to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing
of this imperfect Account of my late
Deareſt and moſt Honour'd Lord, then ſome
comfortable Hopes, which aroſe within Me,
that it might be a means to provoke and haſten
ſome other to draw up a juſt and compleat Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory
of His Lordſhips Life. For theſe papers
are ſuch, as they cannot foreſtall, but may well
Incourage and quicken a performance ſo deſire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
in its ſelf, ſo due to the <hi>Biſhop's</hi> memory,
and ſo profitable for the Publick.</p>
            <p>That I have inſcrib'd them to Your Lordſhips
Name, I hope, My Lord, You can eaſily par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,
becauſe You could not expect that it ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:65451:4"/>
be otherwiſe: Nothing of this kind can be
ſo properly offer'd to any other as to Your ſelf:
You were that Great Prelat's moſt intimate and
many ways indeared Friend; You are his moſt
Worthy and wiſh'd for Succeſſour; You tread
in his ſteps and moſt happily Imitate his Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues:
In all things You appear a Prelate after
his own heart, the very Perſon, whom (had
it been in His power) the Holy Man would
have named, to that Honour, before any other
in the World.</p>
            <p>That Your Lordſhip may live long for the
further Service and Benefit of the Church, and
to the manifold increaſe of Honour and Happineſs
to Your Self both in this and a better World, is
the daily Hearty Prayer of, My Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips moſt obliged<lb/>
and Dutifull Servant<lb/>
HUMF. GOWER.</signed>
               <dateline>S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
                  <hi>John's College</hi>
in <hi>Cambridge</hi>
                  <date>Febr. 12. 1684/5</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:65451:4"/>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>II. KINGS 2. 11, 12.</bibl>
                  <p>And it came to paſs as they ſtill went on and talked, that
behold, there appeared a Chariot of fire, and horſes of
fire, and parted them both aſunder, and Elijah went up
by a whirlwind into heaven.</p>
                  <p>And Eliſha ſaw it, and he cried, My father, my father, the
chariot of Iſrael, and the horſemen thereof: and he ſaw
him no more, and he took hold of his own clothes, and
rent them in two pieces.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THis Church hath ſo lately loſt a Prophet,
and a Father, I mean a moſt Venerable
and holy Biſhop, and theſe words do ſo
expreſly commemorate ſuch a loſs; that I can eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
believe you to be already in ſome apprehenſion
of a diſcourſe on that ſad ſubject. And indeed,
prepare to renew your mourning. If you have bin
yet able to make any truce with your ſorrows for
ſo ineſtimable a loſs, you are like now to have
occaſion to break it off, and to return a while to
funeral and melancholy meditations. I fear I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
touch, tho' never ſo gently, that tender part
without being troubleſome and grievous unto you;
and ſomewhat unſeaſonable too, now that your
breach is ſo happily repair'd, and good amends
made you for what you have lately ſuffer'd: And
yet I muſt venture it. I can forbear no longer,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:65451:5"/>
               <hi>I have held my tongue hitherto and kept ſilence, even from
good words, but it was pain and grief to me.</hi> A great
man is faln amongſt us; and ſhall none of us cry
out, and lift up his voice in weeping and mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
and go before the people, and lead them on,
and teach them how to be affected, how to expreſs
their ſorrows at the Grave of ſo Honourable and
Renowned a Perſon? It may be ſome ſatisfaction
to me, and not unprofitable to you, to ſpend this
hour (my <hi>firſt</hi> before you in this place, ſince that
mournfull day) in conſidering and diſcourſing of
that great common calamity, which then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fell
us.</p>
            <p>What tho' it coſt us <hi>ſome</hi> freſh tears? Our <hi>whole</hi>
ſtock is not ſufficient worthily to expreſs all the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees
and particulars of our loſs: It can never be
better ſpent: You ſcarce ever had, ever can have
juſter and greater matter for repeated and even
perpetual lamentation; <hi>You,</hi> I ſay, of this Church,
of this City and Dioceſs. For God has lately ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
from you your Biſhop, a Prophet, a Paſtour
of his own ſending, and after his own heart;
<hi>a ſpiritual Father, a vigilant Guide and Guardian of your
ſouls: You have loſt an excellent Governour, a watchfull
Overſeer, a faithfull Inſtructour, an able Pilot, an affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
Friend, a charitable Neighbour, an hoſpitable Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainer,
and a bountifull Benefactour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus much, at the leaſt is <hi>yours:</hi> this is <hi>your</hi>
ſhare in the publick Calamity that we now de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plore:
publick, I ſay; for ſo it is, if ever the
death of a ſingle man and a ſubject can be
ſuch. It is not a private and domeſtick ſorrow,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:65451:5"/>
not the mourning of one place or people, that I
now invite you to: there is not a good man alive,
that knew this Biſhop, but laments his death. Were
the greatneſs of the loſs as generally known and as
well underſtood, as it is certain and ſad, there
would be as many mourners for this death, as there
are Chriſtians in the world, and a lamentation
as <hi>Univerſal</hi> as the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church. Therefore,
when we diſcourſe of this late <hi>Great</hi> man, when in
Him we lament our loſs, it will become us to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain
reſentments, and frame expreſſions, as near
as we can, ſuitable to <hi>his</hi> worth, and <hi>our</hi> ſenſe of
it. There can be no danger of being too exceſſive
in our weeping and mourning; whilſt our Grief is
Chriſtian, and that we <hi>ſorrow not</hi> as men without
<hi>hope:</hi> nor can the expreſſions of it be extravagant,
whilſt they endeavour to ſignifie no more then a
loſs as great as could well happen by the death of
<hi>one</hi> man.</p>
            <p>It is one of the leaſt conſiderations that we can
have of him, that he was <hi>ours:</hi> If we will lament
becomingly at this Tomb, our cry muſt be double,
like that of <hi>Eliſha</hi> in my Text, it muſt mount apace,
riſe ſtill higher, and expreſs more and more abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly
in every note; <hi>My father, my father, the cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riot
of Iſrael and the horſemen thereof. Eliſha,</hi> you hear,
claims the intereſt of a <hi>ſon</hi> in the departing Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet:
And I have reaſon to think that thoſe of
this Church and Dioceſs had as good cauſe to love
and Reverence their late Biſhop as a <hi>Father,</hi> as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
Congregation ever had ſo to eſteem their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtour;
ſince any leſs then Apoſtles have bin em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
to feed and govern the Chriſtian Flock:
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:65451:6"/>
But <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſoon paſſes from ſo private and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar
a conſideration to the much more conſiderable
intereſt, which the publick had in that wondrous
man. <hi>The chariot of Iſrael and the horſemen thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that is it, which, in the caſe before us, is
moſt to be regarded. We have loſt a Father, 'tis
true, and ſuch a one as your own memories and
happy experience can better repreſent unto you then
the beſt of words, or the moſt affectionate and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantagious
report, that can be made. But even
that, which ſeems ſo much <hi>yours,</hi> muſt likewiſe be
accounted to the <hi>Church:</hi> He could not have been
ſuch a beneficial <hi>Father</hi> to you, had he not been as
uſefull and as excellent a <hi>Son</hi> to the Holy Church:
All that we can ſay or think to imbitter our own
particular ſhare in this loſs does but inhance and
aggravate that much more deplorable of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.
For in your late holy Prelate the whole Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
Church of God on Earth, but in an eſpecial
manner, this bleſſed part of it, the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi>
did enjoy whatever almoſt could be Good
and Great in a Chriſtian and a Scholar. He liv'd
and dy'd the great Inſtance and Example of his age
of extraordinary natural Endowments moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully
improv'd, vaſt Learning grac'd with the
greateſt Modeſty, incomparable worth and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found
Humility. In him hath the Church loſt one
of the moſt perfect patterns of a Chriſtian Biſhop
that She ever had: Furniſh'd he was with all the
Gifts and Graces, that are requiſite to make a man
moſt amiable and uſefull. His unfeigned and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary
piety, devout and holy Life, his ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and comprehenſive underſtanding, lively and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:65451:6"/>
quick apprehenſion, ready and retentive memory,
His ſolid judgement, unwearied induſtry, and, an
effect of theſe, His accurate and almoſt Univerſal
Knowledge, eſpecially in that which is the end and
perfection of all, the Doctrine of the Holy Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures
and the whole ſacred Text, as they render'd
him the wonder and delight of all that knew him,
whilſt he was here; ſo (it is to be hoped) thoſe
Great Accompliſhments have ſhed abroad ſuch
happy influences in this Kingdom as will not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh
with the preſent age, but ſpread and propa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate
to ſucceeding times, and both to us and our
lateſt poſterity bring forth fruit for the uſe and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit
of the Church.</p>
            <p>And here, methinks, I am willing to enjoy with
you, a while, the refreſhment of this comfortable,
and well grounded hope; and thence to take occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
to alter my ſtile a little, and to ſpeak of the
Churches gain rather then Her loſs, to congratu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late
as well as condole with Her on the account
of this great man. For the Lives of ſuch men as
He, even after death, like the blood of Martyrs,
give nouriſhment and increaſe to the Church:
Their fame and <hi>memory</hi> remains, when they are gone,
and ſhall be for ever <hi>bleſſed.</hi> As they were
<hi>honour'd in their Generation and were the glory of their
times, ſo have they left a name behind them, that their
praiſes might be reported;</hi> And with that name an
Example too, which will live tho' they are dead:
And thoſe their Praiſes and good Examples are moſt
powerfull exhortations to ſuitable practice and imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation.
Their good <hi>actions</hi> are ſo many good <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,</hi>
backt and ſeconded by the beſt motive, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:65451:7"/>
the moſt perſuaſive and convincing application.
'Tis thus that Holy Church enjoys Her Biſhop
ſtill, and I hope ever will, by the bleſſed effects of his
eminent abilities and exemplary Life; tho' He
himſelf is gone and is ſeen no more. And it is thus
that he being <hi>dead yet ſpeaketh,</hi> and teaches more pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully
from the Grave, then he could formerly
from the Pulpit. For his <hi>Life</hi> was a better <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
then He or any man elſe could ever preach. A
meer repetition of the chief Heads of it fully and
faithfully perform'd, would furniſh you out a much
more uſefull one then <hi>this</hi> of mine, haſty notes and
imperfect, and moſtly taken at a diſtance, and, by
the ſhortneſs of the time, now to be made ſhorter.
It muſt be a juſter account, that muſt duly inform the
world with what an excellent ſpirit He was indued,
how full of God and all good things, how conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiouſly
and faithfully He ſpent his hours, how in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duſtrious
he was in private, and how laborious in
publick, how covetouſly He hoarded up, and yet,
how liberally He ſcattered abroad the richeſt trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
of knowledge Humane and Divine, how ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lily
He taught, and as holily liv'd.</p>
            <p>By this great inſtance, amongſt others, the world
may ſee and be convinced that a man may be as
great and good in this, as in any other age of
Chriſtianity. That the higheſt and moſt Heroical
repreſentations of virtue are not meer ſcheme and
fiction, but very real and practicable things; ſuch
as may be indeed reach'd and effectually attain'd.
For theſe did all live and appear and flouriſh in the
Holy Prelate, whom you lately loſt, and we now
lament. In him we have ſeen plainly and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:65451:7"/>
exemplifi'd what before (perhaps) we had
only read in the Rule, conceiv'd in Theory or I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dea,
or could apprehend and fancy as moſt deſirable
and lovely in the Character of a Biſhop. All which
being well conſider'd, I hope I may be allow'd to
inſiſt on this Illuſtrious inſtance of glorifi'd <hi>Elias,</hi>
and the words of his renowned Succeſſour <hi>Eliſha,</hi> as
being ſuch as may very eaſily be accommodated to
our preſent buſineſs, and may help us to meditations
proper for this occaſion.</p>
            <p>For what is the death of Saints but their en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance
into glory? Every good man, at his death,
aſcends as really, tho' not as viſibly as <hi>Elijah,</hi> and
is made as certainly happy as he. Their bodies, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed,
go down to the Grave, and mingle again
with the duſt, from whence they were taken, ſo
to remain till the happy hour of an indiſſoluble
reunion to their ſouls ſhall conſummate the bliſs
of which that better part had taken poſſeſsion im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately
after it was diſlodged from the body:
the ſpirit ſprings upwards as ſoon as ever it feels it
ſelf free from the clog and weight that preſs'd it
down: the ſoul of every Saint mounts as ſwiftly
towards Heaven as <hi>Elijah</hi> himſelf, tho' carried up in
a flaming Chariot with Horſes of fire. Therefore
well and wiſely has the Church choſen to celebrate
the day of their death, as the happieſt and moſt
memorable of their lives; and ſuch as better de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd
to be accounted (as it was ſtil'd) their <hi>birth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day,</hi>
then that, on which they were born into the
world. For then they truly begin to <hi>live</hi> when to
us they <hi>die:</hi> Whenas, that which we commonly
call our Birth, is indeed but the firſt ſtep we take
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:65451:8"/>
in our advance to death: There is a ſhort paſſage
between the womb and immortality, call'd life; but
indeed it lies all along in the region of Death,
to which we are inrol'd ſubjects as ſoon as we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
on that path of mortality, and are not a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
free from the malignant influences of his do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion,
till we are got to the end of it, and have
ſhelter'd our bodies in the Grave, and our ſouls in
the hands of him that gave them. Then, and not
before, are we freed from the imperfections and
incumbrances of fleſh and blood, from all the hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
ſnares, the ſilent and ſecret incroachments of
Death, who begins its approaches as ſoon as we
begin to live: for then he firſt finds us on his own
ground, and within his reach, and inſtantly quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries
upon his prey: <hi>As ſoon as we were born we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan
to draw to our end:</hi> And there is no ſtanding
ſtill in this walk of Death; <hi>for man that is born of
a woman never continueth in one ſtay:</hi> He that lives
moſt healthfully dies daily: <hi>In the midſt of life we
are in death,</hi> and every moment ripens us for the
Grave; to which we are ſtill poſting as faſt as the
wings of time can carry us. Our very health is a
kind of ſickneſs, and whilſt we ſeem to gather
ſtrength and lay up plenty of proviſion to prevent
the ruine or decay of our frail nature, we are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
all that while, but making further advances
towards our latter end: Death is at work as well
as we. In vain do we endeavour to intrench and
fortifie againſt the aſſaults of that obſtinate and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relenting
enemy. An enemy it is that cannot fail
of victory either by undermining or by ſtorm, by
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:65451:8"/>
lingring conſumptions or more acute and violent
diſtempers. Death will certainly demoliſh our
ſtrongeſt hold, and eaſily reduce the tottering ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle,
which we poſſeſs and would ſtill gladly
defend, to ruine and rubbiſh, duſt and aſhes, out
of which it was firſt rear'd, and to which, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to its Makers doom, it muſt return by an una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voidable
diſſolution. But when we are once ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd
at that period, and have received the laſt
blow of Death, and happily paſs'd the common
Gate of Mortality, we are no longer in its power:
For what is ſaid of the <hi>Head</hi> is true of the <hi>members;</hi>
That being once dead they <hi>die no more,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 6. 9.</note> 
               <hi>death hath no
more dominion over</hi> them. That then is the bleſſed
hour, that compleatly delivers the ſons of men,
<hi>who through fear of death, were all their life time ſubject
unto bondage.</hi> It is at that <hi>fatal</hi> moment, as it is
call'd, which ſeems to reduce us to the loweſt,
moſt lamentable and helpleſs condition, that the
Righteous man firſt feels his ſhackles fall off, and
himſelf ſet free, far out of the reach of the malice
of Men or Devils. For by dying he has overcome
his <hi>laſt enemy</hi> which <hi>is death.</hi> Strange victory! But
yet certain; ſuch almighty efficacy in it ſelf, and
ſuch a quickning influence on his <hi>members</hi> has the
Death of our <hi>Head</hi> the Lord <hi>Chriſt;</hi> who having
firſt himſelf overcome it, teaches and enables us to
triumph in Death over Death it ſelf.</p>
            <p>'Tis true the victory is not, in all reſpects, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat,
till we have deſtroy'd and ſpoil'd, as well
as vanquiſh'd, this <hi>King of Terrors:</hi> But that laſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy
cannot be ſo abſolutely ſubdued till the laſt
day, when Death ſhall be <hi>ſwallowed up in victory;</hi> that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:65451:9"/>
is finally and for ever; ſo ſlain as never to revive;
for after that, it ſhall <hi>be no more:</hi> Then likewiſe
ſhall the little victory of the grave be blaſted,
and the poor remains, we left behind us, wreſted
out of the jaws of Death, and reſtored to us: But
how? Not worſted and worn, as they were by
courſe lodging in the duſt, and long captivity in
the dark dungeons of the Earth; but all freſh and
new, and wonderfully changed for the better:
That which was <hi>ſwon in corruption</hi> will be <hi>rais'd
in incorruption.</hi> Its <hi>diſhonour</hi> will be turn'd into
<hi>glory,</hi> and its <hi>weakneſs</hi> into <hi>power;</hi> of a <hi>natural</hi> body,
as we left it, it will be rais'd and preſented to us all
over <hi>ſpiritual</hi> and <hi>heavenly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame indeed, we had before: For tho' it
be moſt true,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15. 50.</note> that <hi>fleſh and blood cannot inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
of God;</hi> that is, as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> immediately ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plains
himſelf, <hi>Corruption</hi> cannot <hi>inherit incorruption;</hi>
yet we know that this mortal muſt be quickned,
and have learn'd to believe the reſurrection of the
<hi>fleſh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 19. 26, 27.</note> and are aſſur'd that we our ſelves, <hi>and not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other</hi>
for us, in our fleſh ſhall ſee God; Even after
<hi>worms</hi> have <hi>deſtroy'd</hi> our bodies.</p>
            <p>It will therefore be the ſame, I ſay; and yet
not that <hi>vile</hi> thing, which once it was, but <hi>chang'd
and faſhioned like unto his glorious body,</hi> who was <hi>the firſt
fruits of them that ſlept,</hi> and who is the <hi>reſurrection and
the life.</hi> Prudent therefore and pious is the Churches
choice in celebrating the <hi>death</hi> under the notion of
the <hi>nativity</hi> of ſuch, to whom <hi>the day of their death</hi>
muſt needs be <hi>better then the day of their birth,</hi> ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
to the obſervation of the <hi>Royal Preacher.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 7. 1.</note> For
then it is, that they are born members of the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:65451:9"/>
Church Triumphant, not only <hi>heirs</hi> but <hi>poſſeſſours</hi> of
Eternal <hi>life.</hi> For they <hi>ſhall not come into condemnation,</hi>
but are actually and properly paſs'd <hi>from death unto
life:</hi> Their Saviour hath wip'd away all tears from
their eyes;<note place="margin">Revel. 21. 4.</note> and to them <hi>there ſhall be no more death,
neither ſorrow nor crying, neither ſhall there be any more
pain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This alone is life properly ſo called; in compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſon
of which, that of this world, which hath u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp'd
the Name, is a very <hi>Death,</hi> only that it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues
longer, is more vexatious and tormenting
then Death it ſelf. Born, indeed, we are, but <hi>unto
trouble,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job 5. 7.</note> 
               <hi>as the ſparks fly upward.</hi> Cares and fears, tears
and temptations, doubts and diſappointments di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract
the mind; whilſt the body, which partakes
in thoſe agonies of the ſoul, is alſo miſerably ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected
to racks and tortures of its own, to pains
and diſeaſes that would be deſperate and inſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
were they not, as it were, the <hi>earneſt</hi> and
<hi>Harbingers</hi> of Death, which puts an end to all
thoſe tragical miſeries of life. And is not this a
goodly thing, for men to be ſo fond of, as gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally
they are, that is it ſelf ſo great a <hi>diſeaſe,</hi> that
nothing but death can <hi>cure?</hi> That therefore is of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten
call'd for, even by thoſe, who yet are much
unprepar'd for ſuch a remedy. But how welcome
then are, or ought to be, the approaches of Death
ſtingleſs! Such it is to thoſe that <hi>die the death of the
righteous,</hi> as <hi>they</hi> all do, to be ſure, that have liv'd
their life; which was well known and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd
by the Holy Prelate, whom I now com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:65451:10"/>
Conſcious to himſelf of a <hi>race</hi> happily <hi>run,</hi> of <hi>ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents</hi>
well <hi>improv'd,</hi> and a <hi>fight</hi> well <hi>fought;</hi> with a
clear conſcience and an undiſturb'd mind, in a well
grounded reliance on the Mercies and Merits of his
Redeemer, the Holy Man, like juſt and devout
<hi>Simeon,</hi> or this very <hi>Elias</hi> in the Text, humbly
pray'd for his departure, in my hearing (as I kneeled
by him) tho', as I have reaſon to believe, againſt
his will, as well as without his knowledge: For
He ſeem'd to mind nothing but his God, his eyes
then ſhut, and his words whiſper'd; tho' both be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
and after he ſpoke ſtrongly and aloud. It was
the only Prayer I ever heard him make, to which
I could not heartily ſay <hi>Amen.</hi> I could have wiſhed
that He ſhould ſtill have <hi>walked before the Lord</hi> in the
Land of the Living, and therefore muſt confeſs
was <hi>afraid</hi> He would be heard, and that God would
not deny him <hi>the requeſt of his lips,</hi> but would <hi>beſtow</hi>
Death upon him; ſo preſſing and importunate was
his Prayer; for He ſeemed to <hi>groan earneſtly,</hi> like S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <hi>Paul,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 5. 2.</note> to have that his <hi>earthly Tabernacle diſſolv'd,</hi>
and to be <hi>cloth'd upon with his houſe from heaven.</hi> And
yet were thoſe breathings of his ſoul ſent up to
Heaven with that ſame <hi>Chriſtian</hi> reſignation and ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion
to the Divine will, which ſo qualifies and
recommends a Good mans Prayers, that they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
fail of a favourable audience and ſucceſs. Thus
He, whoſe Converſation had been ſo much in <hi>Heaven,</hi>
even whilſt Himſelf was on <hi>Earth,</hi> did <hi>in heart and mind
thither aſcend,</hi> even before his ſoul could get looſe from
the troubleſome embraces of the body: And thus like
<hi>Elijah,</hi> He was not only <hi>carried,</hi> but <hi>went</hi> up to Heaven.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:65451:10"/>
That Holy <hi>Prophet</hi> gladly mounted up into his
Heavenly Chariot, leaving moſt willingly <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
and the world below: The whirlwind it ſelf was
not in more haſte then He; the Chariot and Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
and Fire could not move quicker and fly ſwif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
then did his own ardent deſires toward his ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
bliſs. So did our dying <hi>Biſhop</hi> joyfully part
with all that He valued here on Earth, and, in <hi>a
chariot of fire,</hi> mounted unto the Heavens; if I may
be allowed ſo to ſtile the <hi>Feavour,</hi> that ſnatch'd him
from us. But if that may ſeem too remote a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taphor;</hi>
I know I can truly ſay, that his ſoul ſtill
ſoared higher and higher in raptures of fervent and
devout deſires of being <hi>diſſolv'd,</hi> and being with God
his <hi>exceeding great Reward.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This, indeed, was moſt like the fire, in which
<hi>Elijah</hi> aſcended unto Heaven: A fire that needed no
fewel but the devout mind that kindled it: A fire
that <hi>burn't</hi> but <hi>conſumed</hi> not: Such a fire as warms
and heats the Holy Angels themſelves, and kindles
thoſe Divine <hi>Miniſters</hi> into <hi>a flaming fire:</hi> And, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps,
<hi>They</hi> were the Chariot and the Horſes in the
Text. Prompt and ready they are to execute all
the commands of their great Maker, and moſt
cheerfully do thoſe <hi>Triumphant</hi> ſpirits of <hi>Heaven</hi> fly
down to ſuccour and aſſiſt Holy men on <hi>Earth</hi>
and promote the happineſs of <hi>Militant</hi> Saints. But
Angels or clouds, or whatever it was, fiery it did
appear; a fit embleme of that <hi>Heroick Zeal</hi> that did
ſo illuſtriouſly diſcover it ſelf and ſhine forth in the
life of that great <hi>Prophet:</hi> A zeal for the honour of
him that ſent him, like that which afterwards, in
a more Divine manner, appear'd in our bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:65451:11"/>
of whom <hi>Elias</hi> himſelf was a type and, in
ſome ſence, a forerunner, as well as the <hi>Baptiſt,</hi> who
came <hi>in his Spirit and Power:</hi> A <hi>zeal</hi> it was, that even
<hi>conſum'd</hi> him, ſtuck nearer and cloſer to him, then
any earthly concern of his own; A zeal that He
durſt own and ſtand to before the <hi>Searcher</hi> and <hi>Judge</hi>
of hearts;<note place="margin">1 Kings 19. 10, 14.</note> 
               <hi>I have been very jealous,</hi> ſaith He, more
then once, <hi>for the Lord God of Hoſts:</hi> It <hi>vex'd his right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eous</hi>
ſoul to ſee the Apoſtacy of a <hi>whole</hi> nation, as
He reckon'd, from God and all goodneſs; <hi>The chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
of Iſrael have forſaken thy covenant, thrown down
thine Altars, and ſlain thy Prophets with the ſword:</hi>
the deſolation of the <hi>Church</hi> lay heavy on the Good
man's heart.</p>
            <p>For <hi>Ahab</hi> walked in the ſins of <hi>Jeroboam;</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 12. 28, &amp;c.</note> who, for
fear <hi>the heart of the people ſhould turn again to their Lord
the king of Judah,</hi> that he might ſecure his uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and eſtabliſh himſelf, thought it neceſſary to
invade the <hi>Religion</hi> as well as the <hi>Government</hi> of the
Nation: And ſo he ſets up Gods of his own, and
made <hi>Prieſts of the loweſt of the people,</hi> ſuch as were
not of the ſons of <hi>Levi;</hi> and therefore, having no
<hi>lawfull Ordination,</hi> uncapable to ſucceed in the <hi>holy
Function;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſe 33.</note> and he ordained <hi>Feaſts</hi> and made <hi>Sacrifices</hi>
according to his own fancy; even as <hi>he had deviſed in
his own heart.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus 48. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Then ſtood up Elias the prophet as fire, and
his word burnt like a lamp,</hi> as it is expreſs'd by the ſon
of <hi>Sirach.</hi> Even then, when there was not a man
on Earth to <hi>ſecond</hi> him, did he couragiouſly keep
his ground, aſſert the <hi>Church</hi> and its cauſe, and
made ſtout and vehement proteſtations againſt the
<hi>Schiſm,</hi> and all their unreaſonable and irreligious
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:65451:11"/>
               <hi>Innovations:</hi> Full of God and the Commiſſion, that
He had from Him, He put himſelf <hi>in the gap,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
the torrent of Apoſtacy that had overrun the
land, boldly rebuk'd vice and called often and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud
both to <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> to return to God and
his Holy <hi>Church.</hi> The haughty and bloody <hi>Jezebel</hi>
with all her cruel inſtruments, and the many hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred
Prophets of <hi>Baal,</hi> and of the groves, <hi>that did
eat at her table,</hi> could not perſuade or fright him from
his <hi>integrity:</hi> ſtill the holy fire was kept alive in his
religious breaſt, and flam'd brightly out, on all
occaſions, into acts of devotion, and zealous un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings
for the honour of his God: This I ſay,
was the fire that ſeems, at the laſt, to have kindled
for him even the wings of <hi>Angels,</hi> and turn'd them
into a flaming <hi>Chariot</hi> and <hi>Horſes,</hi> with which He
aſcended unto a place of Bliſs prepared for him;
according to that in the firſt of the <hi>Maccabees:
Elias for being zealous and fervent for the Law,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Maccab. 2. 58.</note> 
               <hi>was taken
up into heaven.</hi> It pleaſed God to reward his ſignal
<hi>piety</hi> with ſignal and ſingular <hi>Honour;</hi> And, for that and
other reaſons beſt known to his Divine wiſdom, He
made him an <hi>exception</hi> from the <hi>general rule,</hi> exempting
him from the common fate of all men, by taking
him up alive to himſelf in a viſible and moſt won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfull
manner.</p>
            <p>It is not my preſent <hi>buſineſs,</hi> nor was it my <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign,</hi>
or at all in my <hi>thoughts,</hi> when I choſe this <hi>Text</hi> for
my Theme, to draw a parallel, betwixt the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet
<hi>Elias</hi> and our late <hi>Biſhop;</hi> And yet I judge this
a proper part of my diſcourſe for the mention of
that holy zeal for God and every good thing, which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:65451:12"/>
was ſo viſible and lovely in that excellent Perſon.
God had inrich'd his mind with many extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary
endowments, which render'd him eminent and
honourable, above moſt of his generation. But no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
deſerv'd and procur'd him a greater venera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and awe from all that knew him, then the
unblemiſhed <hi>ſanctity</hi> of his life, his <hi>zeal</hi> for God and
our moſt Holy Religion, and his own ſteddy, uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form,
and exemplary <hi>obedience</hi> to thoſe Evangelical
precepts, which he ſo faithfully preached and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commended
unto others. The day would fail me,
before I could recite the many Evidences and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances
that may be given of what I ſay. But it is
not my buſineſs to write the Great man's <hi>Life,</hi> as
<hi>he</hi> muſt, and that, very voluminouſly, who under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takes
to do him <hi>right</hi> in this particular. His diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes,
deſigns, endeavours, undertakings, his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours
and his ſtudies, almoſt every thing that he did
or ſaid, capable of expreſſing the piety of the heart,
diſcover'd the Holy frame of his Spirit, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly
prov'd to thoſe that convers'd with him,
what <hi>Elijah's</hi> miracle did to the widdow of <hi>Sarepta,</hi>
that he was <hi>a man of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 17. 24.</note> and that <hi>the word of the Lord
was in his mouth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor could ſo ſincere a Piety towards <hi>God</hi> be in
the <hi>Biſhop</hi> any more then in the <hi>Prophet</hi> without a
ſuitable love and religious regard to his <hi>Holy Church.</hi>
But this was ſo eminent in our Prelate, and is ſo
famouſly known at home and abroad, and his prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,
on this account, are ſo acknowledg'd and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd
<hi>in all our Gates,</hi> that I ſhall not need to juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie
this part of his <hi>Character,</hi> by alledging here any
of the very many inſtances of his zeal in oppoſing
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:65451:12"/>
the attempts of the late <hi>Schiſm</hi> and <hi>Rebellion.</hi> He did
not forbear to <hi>proteſt publickly</hi> againſt the <hi>Faction</hi>
even when it was moſt <hi>formidable:</hi> And in a Sermon
preach'd before the Univerſity in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Maries</hi> Church
in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> He urged them vehemently and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincingly
to publiſh a formal <hi>proteſtation</hi> againſt the
<hi>Rebellious League.</hi> And they to whom he ſpoke were
ſufficiently diſpos'd to comply and cloſe with ſo
<hi>Chriſtian</hi> and <hi>Loyal</hi> an exhortation. For the ſpirit
of Error and Deluſion, of Faction and Fury, which
had long before broke looſe and ravaged far and
near, confounding and ſubverting all Orders of men
and things, had not been able to poiſon or cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt
that bright and wholeſome <hi>Fountain</hi> of <hi>Learning</hi>
and <hi>Religion,</hi> tho' ſituated in the midſt of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies
quarters, and perpetually ſurrounded and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſted
with boiſterous Troops of <hi>Rebels.</hi> The good
Work was therefore preſently begun and ſoon fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd;
But could not be publiſhed in the name
of the whole Corporation, and conſequently not
at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> becauſe <hi>one</hi> man, who alone could hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
it, would not permit it to be done. But I have
not only <hi>Charity</hi> enough to hope, but ſufficient <hi>Reaſon</hi>
to believe, that He ſoon repented of the oppoſition
He had made, and became quite of another mind.
But however, printed it was, tho' moſt of the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion
was ſeiz'd at <hi>London,</hi> before it could get
abroad; And this Renowned Nurſery of <hi>Learning</hi>
and <hi>Loyalty</hi> did not looſe the honour of getting the
ſtart of her equal Siſter, and giving her an excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent
pattern and encouragement by ſo early and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable
an undertaking.</p>
            <p>In this conſcientious zeal for the Church, did our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:65451:13"/>
Biſhop and many others, to their laſting comfort
and Renown, faithfully perſevere, to the loſs of
all they had in this world, but their lives: And
thoſe <hi>lives,</hi> which God gave them <hi>for a prey,</hi> were
cheap and vile in their own eyes in competition
with their <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Religion;</hi> for which the <hi>Biſhop</hi>
was ready and reſolv'd, and (ſometimes) very
likely to reſiſt even <hi>unto blood.</hi> Every place, where
this Good man ſojourn'd, after He was driven from
his ſtudy in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> can furniſh out various evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dences
of his pious and reſtleſs endeavours for the
benefit of the publick. His time was always uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
ſpent, in <hi>confirming</hi> thoſe that ſtood, <hi>ſupporting</hi>
them that were falling, <hi>raiſing up</hi> them that were
down, <hi>encouraging</hi> the faint-hearted, and <hi>reducing</hi>
them that were gone aſtray. In the very worſt of
times, when the <hi>Rebellion</hi> was <hi>rampant,</hi> and the <hi>bloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
Uſurper</hi> had <hi>kill'd and taken poſſeſſion,</hi> then did our
<hi>Elijah,</hi> even in <hi>Samaria,</hi> in the <hi>Rebels Metropolis,</hi> in
ſpite of all their menaces and malice, couragiouſly
ſtand up, and in words aſſert, and in practice per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form
his duty to God and to the <hi>Church:</hi> And to
him gladly flock'd Loyal multitudes of Religious
and true hearted people, to celebrate thoſe Holy
Offices (to which they were by Law obliged) in
<hi>private houſes,</hi> when by armed violence they were for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
out and driven from the <hi>Churches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, can you believe that this <hi>Heroick</hi> Inſtance
of <hi>Primitive Chriſtian Loyalty and Zeal,</hi> could be alledg'd
for the juſtification of <hi>Factious</hi> and <hi>Schiſmatical Conven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles?</hi>
But what hath not been ſaid and done to
give life and countenance to the beloved, tho' de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:65451:13"/>
Cauſe? It might have been hoped that
ſuch an inſtance of integrity and honeſt perſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance
in obedience to the <hi>Church,</hi> in a time of <hi>tryal</hi>
and <hi>danger,</hi> would have wrought ſome relenting in
Her perſecutors, and made them more mindfull
of their own duty for the future. But inſtead of
that, the thing has been repreſented as an argument
or defence for the <hi>illegal meetings</hi> of <hi>Nonconformiſts.</hi>
One would think this could not be intended for
good earneſt: but be that as it will, I am ſure
the <hi>Biſhops</hi> anſwer was very ingenious and appoſite;
and it was to this purpoſe, <hi>that, as our preſent So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vereign
was rightfull King of</hi> England, <hi>even when hid
in the</hi> Royal oak, <hi>and</hi> Cromwell <hi>an Uſurper, tho' at</hi>
Whitehall <hi>and in the Throne; ſo was He a regular Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher,
and his meeting at</hi> Exeter-houſe <hi>a true Congregation,
of the Church of</hi> England; <hi>whenas the Objectour tho' prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching
at</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls Croſs, <hi>would be ſtill a ſchiſmatick, and
His aſſembly of Separatiſts a Conventicle even in the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thedral
Church of</hi> Canterbury, <hi>or</hi> S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Pauls <hi>in</hi>
London.</p>
            <p>But thus as I was ſaying, did this <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> man
<hi>endure hardſhip as a good Souldier of Jeſus Chriſt. God
having not given him the Spirit of Fear, but of Power, of
Love, and of a Sound mind.</hi> Like his <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter</hi>
He went about doing good, <hi>in meekneſs inſtructing
thoſe that oppos'd themſelves;</hi> and was <hi>inſtant in ſeaſon and
out of ſeaſon reproving, rebuking, exhorting with all long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuffering
and Doctrine.</hi> Thus ſpent he his days of
mourning, either privately <hi>wreſtling</hi> with his God in
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:65451:14"/>
Prayer for <hi>the remnant of Iſrael;</hi> that He would <hi>turn
the Captivity</hi> of his people, and be <hi>favourable and gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious
unto Sion, and build up the walls of Jeruſalem;</hi> or
in publick <hi>contending</hi> with the enemies of the <hi>Church;</hi>
diſputing both in publick and private with the moſt
Powerfull and skilfull of the Adverſaries of both
kinds, <hi>Romaniſts</hi> and others; with equal zeal and
knowledge, convincing or confounding the gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayers.
For He was a <hi>Workman</hi> that needed <hi>not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhamed.</hi>
God had given him many talents, and
grace to improve them, ſo that as none could be
more deſirous, neither was there any more able to
ſerve the Church then Himſelf. Once He was
ſeiz'd whilſt He was in theſe Holy Exerciſes, and
by ſpecial Order carried before the <hi>Uſurper</hi> himſelf:
who expoſtulated with him as <hi>Ahab</hi> did with
<hi>Elijah,</hi> as a <hi>troubler</hi> of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> But then ſo affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nately
and ſolidly did the <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> man, like S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <hi>Paul</hi> before <hi>Felix,</hi> reaſon of thoſe things, for which
He was call'd in queſtion; that, whether the
wretch that heard him, had ſence enough left to
make him <hi>tremble,</hi> or no; certainly, he was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to reſiſt the <hi>wiſdom</hi> and the <hi>ſpirit</hi> by which he
ſpake; but, having vouchſaf'd to beſtow ſome few
good words on the <hi>Church-Prayers,</hi> ſent away the
Good man, without uſing any further violence,
at the preſent.</p>
            <p>But thus far have I been carried by the Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration
of that Holy Fire of Zeal which flam'd
in <hi>Elijah's</hi> breaſt, to ſpeak of that which was ſo
plainly diſcernable in our late Prelate. But leave
we now that bleſſed <hi>Prophet</hi> to the happy rewards
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:65451:14"/>
of his Love and Labours, and leave gazing too at
his wondrous aſcent, the <hi>Whirlwind,</hi> the <hi>Fire</hi> and
<hi>Flames,</hi> the <hi>Chariot</hi> and <hi>Horſes</hi> that conveyed him
ſtrangely and ſafely to ſome of the <hi>many manſions</hi> in
the Fathers houſe. And let us look down a while
and obſerve and liſten to the behaviour and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation
of the forſaken and deſolate <hi>Eliſha.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Eliſha</hi> was the <hi>humble Friend,</hi> both the <hi>companion</hi> and
<hi>ſervant</hi> of <hi>Elijah:</hi> He was <hi>Prophet-elect,</hi> being, by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine
direction and deſignation, to ſucceed his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</hi>
But why ſhould he lament then? Why this
outcry when his <hi>Maſter</hi> was taken from him? Was
there any thing ſo ſad and grievous to either of the
two in this tranſlation, that might juſtly provoke
<hi>Eliſha</hi> to ſuch a tranſport of grief as he ſeemed to
expreſs when he <hi>cried out, and took hold of his own clothes
and rent them in two pieces?</hi> He himſelf well knew,
and had been reminded by other ſons of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,
often enough, of what would happen, and
he expected it at that time, and was come thither
reſolv'd to be preſent at it: <hi>Elias</hi> himſelf could
not perſwade him to ſtay behind; ſo that there
could be no great ſurprize in the caſe. Beſides, it
was a very glorious <hi>Exit</hi> for his <hi>Maſter,</hi> whom he
ſaw in State and Triumph aſcending up towards
Heaven. Here was no room, one would think,
for ſorrow, no reaſon for lamentation; No ſick
bed nor dying groans; Nothing of agony or pain,
nor ought of that ghaſtly <hi>pomp</hi> of Death, that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly
renders the paſſage to the other ſtate ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible
and uneaſie, even to the beſt of men, and
very uncomfortable and grievous to their friends.
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:65451:15"/>
Or was it for himſelf that <hi>Eliſha</hi> thus laments, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
now he had loſt his <hi>Maſter,</hi> who was taken
<hi>from his head,</hi> and therefore could no longer aſſiſt
him by his preſence and advice? But what loſs
could that be to him, who had the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi>
for his aſſiſtance, was a <hi>Prophet</hi> himſelf, and now
that <hi>Elijah</hi> was gone, the <hi>Principal</hi> and <hi>Father</hi> of
them all?</p>
            <p>But well might He grieve for all this: Not,
indeed, on the account of his <hi>Maſter,</hi> in whoſe caſe
there was nothing at all diſmal or deplorable, but
for himſelf, and for the publick, there was much
matter of ſorrow: And thoſe conſiderations of a
juſt grief ſeem to be expreſſed in the <hi>Phraſes</hi> of his
lamentation: <hi>My father, my father, The chariot of
Iſrael and the horſemen thereof.</hi> The <hi>firſt</hi> ſpeaks (as
we have obſerved already) his own private intereſt
in the <hi>Prophet.</hi> He had loſt a Guide and Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour,
a faithfull and able Teacher and Director:
And ſuch are very frequently and deſervedly ſtil'd
<hi>Fathers</hi> in Holy Writ; and accordingly they that
are ſo taught and govern'd are call'd <hi>Sons;</hi> as ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral
times in this very <hi>Chapter,</hi> as well as in other
places. The Spirit of God indeed, could, and would,
and did abundantly ſupply <hi>Eliſha</hi> with all things ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
for his <hi>Prophetick</hi> Office. But ſtill he had loſt
a ſure Friend, a pious Companion and wiſe Guide
of his life; and that's enough to make his mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
appear decent, and to juſtifie all the expreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
of his ſorrow. But <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſtops not at this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flexion
on his own loſs: That conſideration was
preſently ſwallowed up by greater. The <hi>Church</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:65451:15"/>
and <hi>Kingdom</hi> had in <hi>Elijah</hi> loſt a main ornament
and ſupport; and that is it, which is expreſs'd in the
following very elegant and ſignificant Phraſes:
<hi>The chariot of Iſrael and the horſemen thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The appearance, which <hi>Eliſha</hi> then had before
his eyes, of a <hi>chariot and horſes of fire,</hi> made the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon
the more ſeaſonable, and might be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
to prompt him to it. But that was not the
only reaſon, if it were at all any occaſion of that
figurative alluſion. It is like he would have us'd
the ſame expreſſion, tho' he had ſeen the <hi>Prophet</hi>
expiring on a <hi>bed,</hi> inſtead of mounting towards
Heaven in a <hi>chariot;</hi> as it was by King <hi>Joaſh</hi> applied
to him himſelf,<note place="margin">2 Kings 13. 14.</note> when <hi>fal'n ſick of his ſickneſs whereof
he died.</hi> The whole world is a looſer by the
death of a good man; more eſpecially then was
that Kingdom and people ſo, by the loſs of ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celling
a perſon as was <hi>Elijah:</hi> This truly was a
becoming argument for the lamentation of a
<hi>Prophet:</hi> For <hi>when the righteous man periſheth,</hi> or is
taken away, tho' others do not, yet, <hi>they</hi> that are
like himſelf will <hi>conſider it, and lay it to heart.</hi> He,
indeed, <hi>hath hope in his death,</hi> and enters into <hi>peace,</hi>
and is refreſh'd and <hi>comforted</hi> in <hi>Abraham's</hi> boſom:
but they that are left behind; they, particularly,
that liv'd near him, within the direct influence of
his good deeds and holy example, are really dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified
by his death; as will ſoon appear by weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the expreſſions, in which <hi>Eliſha</hi> here bemoan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
the publick loſs in the perſon of the great
<hi>Elijah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The chariot of Iſrael and the horſemen thereof.</hi> A <hi>Metaphor</hi>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:65451:16"/>
taken from <hi>war,</hi> and ſo very aptly beſtowed upon
a <hi>Champion</hi> of the Church <hi>Militant. Chariots</hi> anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently
were, and <hi>Horſemen</hi> ſtill are a main ſtrength
and protection to a people, to defend them from,
and prevent, as alſo to repell and ſuppreſs the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſults
and invaſions of their enemies. Formidable
was the force of Chariots of war in the land of
<hi>Canaan,</hi> when the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> came to diſpoſſeſs the
former inhabitants, and to plant themſelves in that
fruitfull countrey: Inſomuch that the houſe of
<hi>Joſeph,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joſh. 17. 16. Verſe 17.</note> tho' a <hi>great people and of great power,</hi> excepted
againſt the portion allotted to them by <hi>Joſhua,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
the enemy, that was in poſſeſſion, had
<hi>chariots of Iron:</hi> and ſo, all along, we find the
power of thoſe Princes expreſs'd by the number of
their <hi>Chariots</hi> and <hi>Horſemen,</hi> both before and after
the conqueſt of the Countrey by the <hi>Iſraelites.</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly,
it is particularly obſerved in the deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption
of <hi>King Solomon's</hi> ſtrength,<note place="margin">2 Chron. 1. 14.</note> that he <hi>gathered Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots
and Horſemen, and had a thouſand and four hundred
Chariots and twelve thouſand Horſemen, which he plac'd in
the Chariot-cities, and with the King at Jeruſalem.</hi> Nay,
the invincible force of the <hi>armies</hi> of the Lord of <hi>Hoſts</hi>
is expreſs'd by the inſpired <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> with an alluſion to
this powerfull proviſion for war; where he ſings
that <hi>the chariots of God are twenty thouſands even thouſands
of Angels;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſalm 68. 17.</note> of which, perhaps, as I noted before, a
party were commanded out to fetch <hi>Elijah,</hi> and
were the ſame that convoy'd that great <hi>Prophet</hi> in
his aſcenſion unto Heaven: For <hi>they are ſent forth to
miniſter for them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 1. 14.</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall be heirs of ſalvation.</hi> But
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:65451:16"/>
there were many more of them appointed after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
for a <hi>Guard</hi> to his ſucceſſour <hi>Eliſha</hi> againſt the
Horſes and Chariots of the <hi>Syrian King;</hi> when at
the Prayer of that Prophet,<note place="margin">2 Kings 6. 17.</note> 
               <hi>the Lord opened the eyes of
the young man</hi> his ſervant, <hi>and he ſaw, and behold the
mountain was full of horſes, and chariots of fire, round a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout
Eliſha.</hi> And perhaps there were <hi>two</hi> armies of
them incamp'd about <hi>Jacob</hi> to keep and conduct
him and his in ſafety in his return to his own
Countrey:<note place="margin">Gen. 32. 1, 2.</note> for it is ſaid <hi>the Angels of God met him,
and he call'd the name of that place Mahanaim;</hi> which <hi>dual</hi>
word may imply that there were <hi>two</hi> Camps or
Companies of that Heavenly Hoſt. So that this
bright <hi>Militia</hi> of Heaven is always ready to execute
the orders of their Soveraign Lord, whether they
be to honour and protect his Loyal Subjects, or
confound his Enemies. And we know what dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
havock and ſlaughter has been made by a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroying
<hi>Angel</hi> in the ſpace of three days, nay even
in a night. The Fire and Chariots and Whirlwind
had orders, as we find in the Text, to attend,
aſſiſt and adorn the Triumphant aſcenſion of <hi>Elias:</hi>
But in another caſe, the very ſame are to be diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch'd
as meſſengers of Gods <hi>wrath,</hi> the Inſtruments
and Executioners of his vengeance.<note place="margin">Iſa. 66. 15.</note> 
               <hi>For behold the
Lord will come with fire and with his chariots like a whirl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wind
to render his anger with fury and his rebuke with flames
of fire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From what hath been ſaid it is evident enough,
that, when <hi>Eliſha</hi> ſtil'd <hi>Elijah the chariot of Iſrael and
the horſemen thereof,</hi> he intended thereby to expreſs
him to be the great <hi>Strength, Defence</hi> and <hi>Support</hi> of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:65451:17"/>
the Kingdom: And ſo he was in a moſt eminent
manner; being extraordinarily commiſſion'd and
impower'd by God to proteſt againſt the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations
and Apoſtacy of that people; and to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour
the reſtitution of Religion, the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of manners, and Eſtabliſhment of Affairs in
the whole Kingdom: In this Office and Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration
<hi>Eliſha</hi> ſucceeded him, and was accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly,
when he lay on his death bed, ſaluted and
acknowledged, as the <hi>chariot and horſemen of Iſrael,</hi> by
the King himſelf, as I obſerved before.</p>
            <p>But not theſe two <hi>extraordinary Prophets</hi> only,
but all the <hi>ſons</hi> of the <hi>Prophets,</hi> all that are ſent by
God, and ſet apart to be Guides and Paſtours of a
people, I ſay all and every of theſe, as far as they
are true to their truſt, and worthily diſcharge their
duty, are <hi>ſtrengths</hi> and <hi>defences</hi> to the places, where
they live, and ſo, in ſome preportion, <hi>the chariot and horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men</hi>
thereof. Nay, ſo is every virtuous and good man,
in ſome degree. <hi>Sodom</hi> it ſelf had eſcaped its ſo
much merited and long provok'd deſtruction, if
<hi>ten</hi> righteous perſons could have been found in
the whole City; And, <hi>one</hi> ſingle Juſt man might
have been ſufficient to have indemnifi'd all <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jer. 5. 1.</note> as appears from the <hi>Prophet Jeremiah.</hi> Every
good man is a publick good: He helps to ſtave
off Judgements and bring down bleſſings upon a
people. Juſt <hi>Lot</hi> ſaved <hi>Zoar,</hi> and the prayers of <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi>
rais'd up again, and repair'd the ruines of
<hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> They have an intereſt and favour in the
Court of Heaven:<note place="margin">Pſal. 34. 17.</note> 
               <hi>The eyes of the Lord are upon the
righteous, and his ears are open to their cry:</hi> They who
make moſt conſcience of their own duty, make
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:65451:17"/>
the beſt Solicitours for others.<note place="margin">John 9. 31.</note> 
               <hi>If any man be a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipper
of God, and doth his will, him he heareth.</hi> And
therefore the <hi>Church</hi> hath always given thanks for
them, as Publick bleſſings, praiſing Almighty
God for the good Examples of <hi>all</hi> Holy men and
women in general, as well as for Biſhops, Prieſts
and Deacons. But ſuch as by their very <hi>Function</hi>
and <hi>office</hi> are Holy to the Lord, ſuch whoſe very
buſineſs it is to bleſs and mediate for the people,
and to guide and teach them; theſe, I ſay, are in
a more eſpecial manner, <hi>Protection and Defence, the
Chariot and Horſemen</hi> unto the Church and Nation,
unto which they do belong: And this they are
chiefly on the account of their <hi>Prayers,</hi> their <hi>Precepts</hi>
and their <hi>Practice.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>GOD is moſt likely to hear the <hi>Interceſſions</hi> of thoſe
whom He Himſelf has appointed to intercede. <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bimelech</hi>
King of <hi>Gerar</hi> was not preſently to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned
on the account of the <hi>Integrity</hi> of his heart,
and the <hi>Innocency</hi> of his hands, which he pleaded,
and was by God, in ſome ſort allowed, but by the
<hi>prayers of Abraham:</hi> God would have his mercy and
bleſſings deſcend in a <hi>regular</hi> way, and what he
might have given out directly and immediately
from himſelf, was not to be beſtowed till the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi>
had <hi>prayed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 20. 7.</note> 
               <hi>Reſtore the man his wife, for he is a
Prophet, and he ſhall pray for thee, and thou ſhalt live.</hi>
When God had denounced heavy Judgements by
his <hi>Prophet Joel</hi> he preſcribes it as one means to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
thoſe impending evils that <hi>Prayers</hi> be made by
the <hi>Prieſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joel 2. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Let the Prieſts the Miniſters of the Lord,
weep between the porch and the Altar.</hi> Nor did S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>James</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:65451:18"/>
think it ſufficient to adviſe the ſick man to pray
for himſelf, but remits him to Gods <hi>officers,</hi> ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
for that purpoſe, the publick <hi>Mediatours</hi> and
<hi>Interceſſours</hi> for the people.<note place="margin">James 5. 14.</note> 
               <hi>Let him call,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>for
the Elders of the Church, and let them pray over him.</hi> But
how very effectual the <hi>fervent prayers</hi> of ſuch men ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
are, appears ſufficiently from the inſtance here
before us of the great <hi>Elijah,</hi> ſingled out by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>James</hi>
for the ſame purpoſe, and alledged ſoon after the
words already cited.<note place="margin">James 5. 17.</note> He, I ſay, who, tho <hi>a man
ſubject to like paſſions as we are,</hi> opened and ſhut the
Heavens at his pleaſure, kept up the <hi>dew</hi> and <hi>rain,</hi>
but brought down ſhowres of <hi>fire;</hi> ſo that all things
hapned <hi>according to</hi> his <hi>word.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Kings 17. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Miniſters of Gods holy Word and Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
in reſpect of one part of their Function,
are Gods Ambaſſadours to the people; but, in this
of <hi>prayer,</hi> they are <hi>their</hi> Agents and Solicitours with
God, conſtituted by himſelf as a ſort of <hi>Mediatours</hi>
for and amongſt men, <hi>Maſters of Requeſts,</hi> reſident
on Earth, appointed to preſent and offer up the pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions
of the people to and in the name of the
<hi>one</hi> great <hi>Mediatour between God and Man:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 2. 5.</note> And to him
thoſe addreſſes cannot but be the more acceptable
as coming in his own Method and way, and thro'
thoſe hands, to which he has committed ſo great
a power as to <hi>bind and looſe in Heaven and on Earth,</hi> a
power not vouchſafed (as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> ſomewhere
expreſſeth it) <hi>either to Angels or Arch-Angels,</hi> or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
of the moſt glorified favourites of Heaven.</p>
            <p>If then perſons ſet aſide and conſecrated for the
<hi>ſervice</hi> of God and his Church be ordinarily accept<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:65451:18"/>
and powerfull Interceſſours; how much does
this Church and Nation, and, indeed, the whole
Chriſtian world owe to the pious Devotions of the
Holy Prelate, of whom we are now ſpeaking!
Twice a day, moſt duly, beſides his family Prayers,
He offer'd up to Heaven, either in the Publick
Congregation, or (when his health could not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
that) more privately, his daily Homage and
Sacrifice of <hi>Morning</hi> and <hi>Evening</hi> Prayer and Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving,
according to the Preſcript of the Church of
<hi>England.</hi> He that had ſo throughly ſtudied and did
ſo perfectly underſtand the Beauties and Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
of the <hi>Engliſh Liturgy,</hi> and ſo frequently and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectionately
recommended the conſcientious and
devout uſe of it to all, both Clergy and others;
and had himſelf received great Spiritual Comfort
and Advantages by a long and Religious atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance
on it: He, I ſay, as you will eaſily believe,
could not allow himſelf in the leaſt neglect of it,
but went to it and called for it as his <hi>daily bread,</hi> the
neceſſary food and refreſhment of his ſoul.</p>
            <p>I need not tell this Congregation, I am ſure,
how Solemn and Reverend his approaches were
to this Sacred place, how Holy and <hi>Saint-like</hi> his
behaviour here. Almoſt every thing that Good
man did or ſaid was edifying and inſtructive; but
nothing could well be more ſo, then his devout de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment,
when he had audience with his God.
The Faith and Fervency, the Humble, yet Reſtleſs and
Irreſiſtible importunity of his Spirit ſtrugling and
contending with God in Prayer could not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd
from thoſe that ſaw him, but flam'd up from
his <hi>heart</hi> into his <hi>eyes,</hi> and diſcover'd it ſelf by ſo
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:65451:19"/>
many natural indications of Holy and tranſported
Affections, that the Example was enough to rouze
and warm the moſt ſluggiſh and frozen Devotion
of any that did obſerve him. It is no wonder that
his devout Soul found ſo Divine a relliſh in thoſe
Prayers, to which He attended with ſo much Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence
and Religion. The <hi>Prayers of the Church</hi> are
a <hi>dead</hi> letter to none but ſuch as bring <hi>dead</hi> hearts
to them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. diſc. 16.</note> as our <hi>Martyr'd Sovereign</hi> obſerved long
ſince. And I dare ſay, that all that uſe them, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
the bleſſed effect be hindred by <hi>prejudice</hi> or <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneſs,</hi>
do experience that thoſe <hi>united and well advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
Devotions</hi> are moſt excellently contriv'd to kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle
and keep alive in us ſuch pious diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
of mind, as are moſt ſuitable to that
duty.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not preſume to conduct you from the
<hi>Church</hi> to the Good mans <hi>Cloſet,</hi> or pretend to reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
how often in a day He was upon his knees.
He that did nothing for oſtentation, and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood
ſo well the Reward reſerv'd for good things
done <hi>in ſecret,</hi> knew how to conceal thoſe Addreſſes
from the eyes of <hi>man,</hi> which He intended only for
the notice of his <hi>God.</hi> But his conſtant and ſteddy
Practice of all Chriſtian duties, the general Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
of his Life, the viſible delight He took in
<hi>Prayer</hi> (that great <hi>Priviledge</hi> as well as <hi>Duty</hi> of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind)
beſides other Evidences, that could not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
be kept from the obſervation of thoſe that
had the honour and happineſs to be near him,
ſerve to aſſure us, that He <hi>watch'd</hi> unto Prayer,
pray'd <hi>always, without ceaſing,</hi> and at <hi>all ſeaſons,</hi> accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
to a due underſtanding of thoſe expreſſions in
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:65451:19"/>
               <hi>Holy Writ.</hi> It was to him a <hi>pleaſant</hi> performance, of
which He could not be weary. What a <hi>Benefactour</hi>
(I ſay) then was He to this <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> which
had ſo great a ſhare in his publick and private Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titions
ſent up to a Gracious God with ſuch an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feigned
Piety and ardent Zeal!<note place="margin">Luke 18. 1.</note> 
               <hi>Shall not God hear his
ſervants that cry day and night unto him?</hi> He that <hi>ask'd</hi>
ſuch a <hi>queſtion</hi> when He was on <hi>Earth,</hi> will be ſure
to <hi>anſwer</hi> ſuch <hi>prayers</hi> now he is in <hi>Heaven.</hi> And
then I am ſure the publick has received manifold
advantage from the <hi>Biſhop's</hi> earneſt ſupplications put
up in the behalf of the whole Kingdom; The
intereſt of which was as dear to him as his own
Soul, and for which He was almoſt hourly breath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
out fervent ejaculations,<note place="margin">Rev. 5. 8.</note> and <hi>night and day pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
exceedingly.</hi> The prayers of <hi>Saints,</hi> we are told,
are as <hi>golden vials full of odours;</hi> and thoſe odours are
ſacrifices of <hi>ſweet ſavour,</hi> unto the God of Heaven.
Such Sacrifices of Supplications, Interceſſions and
giving of Thanks, was this Holy Prelate almoſt
conſtantly offering up unto Almighty God,
for the <hi>King</hi> and all in <hi>Authority,</hi> for the <hi>Holy Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick
Church,</hi> and for <hi>all Men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Three moſt ſignal Favours and Bleſſings on this
Land within our memories I have often heard his
Lordſhip mention with moſt feeling and affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
expreſſions of Religious Gratitude and Joy.
The <hi>firſt</hi> was that <hi>Abundance</hi> of Heavenly <hi>Graces</hi> which
adorn'd the Perſon of our late <hi>Martyr'd Sovereign,</hi> and
thoſe particularly which did ſo Gloriouſly ſhine
forth in him under the moſt barbarous indignities
and bloody violence offer'd him by the <hi>Rebels:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:65451:20"/>
Another</hi> was that ſtupendous revolution of Affairs
brought about by the miraculous Providence of
God in the <hi>Reſtitution</hi> of His preſent <hi>Majeſty</hi> and the
<hi>Church</hi> in Honour and Peace, to the aſtoniſhment
and confuſion of the Adverſaries of <hi>them Both.</hi> The
<hi>Third</hi> was the wonderfull diſappointment and moſt
happy Diſcovery of the late <hi>Fanatical</hi> and <hi>Republican</hi>
Conſpiracy againſt the Life of His Sacred <hi>Majeſty</hi>
and His <hi>Royal</hi> Brother. And to theſe He added that
more Publick and General Mercy of God in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing
ſo ſeaſonably and ſo mightily for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence
of our common <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> by putting a hook
in the Noſtrils of the <hi>Turkiſh Leviathan,</hi> and pulling
him back again, and humbling him even to the
duſt; when he ſeemed to himſelf and us in poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
of his prey, and to have little to do but to
<hi>kill and eat.</hi> Theſe were Bounties and Largeſſes of
Heaven, that fill'd the heart of the Holy <hi>Biſhop</hi> with
daily <hi>Hallelujahs:</hi> He could hardly ever ſpeak of them
without tears of Joy: And doubtleſs they relliſhed
the more comfortably to his Soul, becauſe he had
reaſon to apprehend them as ſo many Gracious re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns
and anſwers to his Prayers.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, That <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes</hi> do again <hi>enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Gates</hi> of our Cities, and the <hi>Regal Throne</hi> is not
diſhonour'd and polluted by <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> that our
<hi>Judges</hi> are reſtored <hi>as at the firſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1. 26.</note> and our <hi>Counſellers as
at the beginning;</hi> that our <hi>Holy Religion</hi> is ſecur'd to us
by the reeſtabliſhment of the moſt <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution
of <hi>this Church;</hi> that we do not <hi>eat our bread
with carefulneſs,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 12. 19.</note> 
               <hi>and drink our water with aſtoniſhment;</hi>
But free from oppreſſion either foreign or dome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:65451:20"/>
we <hi>do</hi> or <hi>may</hi> lead quiet and peaceable lives
in all Godlineſs and honeſty: All this, I ſay, and
all elſe in this world, that is or ought to be dear
to <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> we owe under God to the fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
Prayers of ſuch Holy Men as this, of whom
we are now ſpeaking: In this reſpect therefore
they are not unworthy of the Compellation in the
Text.<note place="margin">Greg. Nyſſ. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Since <hi>Prayer</hi> it ſelf is ſuch ſure <hi>armour and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence,</hi>
ſuch a <hi>ſhield and buckler,</hi> and mighty Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
both day and night, as we know it is, the
Holy Men that are aſſiduous in this devout exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe,
and expert managers of ſo powerfull a wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon
of our <hi>Chriſtian warfare</hi> may well be eſteemed
the <hi>Chariot and Horſemen;</hi> that is, a great ſtrength
and defence to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> in which they
live, and for which moſt eſpecially they are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd.</p>
            <p>BUT ſuch they are ſtill on another account; and
that is, as they <hi>labour in the word and doctrine;</hi> when
to their <hi>Prayers</hi> they add <hi>Precepts,</hi> and joyn <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi>
to their <hi>Interceſsion:</hi> By <hi>one</hi> they prepare and
beſpeak Mercies; by the <hi>other</hi> they qualifie the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
and make them capable to receive them: The
choiceſt Bleſſings of <hi>this</hi> life, will turn <hi>at laſt</hi> to no
comfortable account, if we are not, by a right
uſe of them, ſomething better'd, and ſo made fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
for <hi>another.</hi> Now theſe men I ſpeak of are to
teach us how to make that Saving Uſe of them;
For they are Meſſengers of God ſent by him with
full Commiſſion and ample Inſtructions to make
known the <hi>the whole will of God for our ſalvation.</hi> It is
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:65451:21"/>
true,<note place="margin">Rom. 10. 13. 14.</note> that <hi>whoever calls upon the name of the Lord ſhall
be ſaved:</hi> But <hi>they</hi> cannot <hi>call</hi> on him that do not
<hi>believe</hi> in him, which they cannot do, unleſs they
have <hi>heard</hi> of him; nor can they hear of him <hi>with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
a Preacher,</hi> and that Preacher muſt be <hi>ſent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nor is this Office of <hi>Teaching</hi> neceſſary only for
the <hi>firſt</hi> publiſhing of the <hi>Goſpel:</hi> Otherwiſe, our
<hi>Saviour</hi> needed not to have aſſur'd his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> as he
did, of his preſence with them and their <hi>Succeſſours
even unto the end of the world:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 28. 20.</note> The Teaching part
of their Office might have been diſpatched in a
few years, if it had been ſufficient for the edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
and eſtabliſhment of the <hi>Church</hi> to have the
foundations of it laid by publiſhing the Chriſtian
Faith to the whole world. But we know that God
gave <hi>Apoſtles,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 4. 11, 12, 13.</note> 
               <hi>Prophets, Evangeliſts, Paſtours and Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
for the perfecting of the Saints, for the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,
for the edifying of the body of Chriſt, till we all come in
the Unity of the Faith, and of the knowledge of the ſon of
God unto a perfect man; unto the meaſure of the ſtature of the
fulneſs of Chriſt.</hi> And that's a work that will be
ſtill in doing, in ſome particulars at leaſt and in
ſome perſons, ſo that we ſhall never be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
enough in this world to ſtand in no need of
our Teachers.</p>
            <p>To them it appertains to <hi>ſtrengthen the diſeaſed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 34. 4.</note> 
               <hi>heal
the ſick, bind up that which is broken, ſeek that which is
loſt, and bring back that which is driven away:</hi> And there
will be ſooner want of <hi>labourers</hi> then <hi>work</hi> for
them in all theſe particulars of their employment.
It is the faithfull Teachers part to deliver to the
people that which He hath <hi>received of the Lord,</hi> to
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:65451:21"/>
withſtand the oppoſtion and contradiction of thoſe
that would obtrude any thing <hi>contrary to the form of
ſound words,</hi> and to <hi>contend earneſtly for the faith once de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered
to the Saints:</hi> He is not only the <hi>Watchman,</hi>
that <hi>obſerves</hi> the approach of the Enemy, but the
<hi>Warriour</hi> alſo and the Guard that <hi>repels</hi> him. He
deſcries afar off and gives notice of all the ſlie ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licious
deſigns and attempts of Hereticks and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>novatours,
all that <hi>lie in wait to deceive,</hi> that would
invade the <hi>vineyard</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> either by open
Violence, or private and Treacherous inſinuations.
He countermines the ſecret and wily workings of
the <hi>Moles</hi> and <hi>Foxes,</hi> as well as fortifies againſt the
furious aſſaults of <hi>wild Boars</hi> and other rampant
Beaſts of prey. He encourageth the Righteous man
to perſevere in the happy courſe that he hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun,
applauds his progreſs in the paths of Piety,
bids him look forward and <hi>preſs on to the mark for the
prize of the high calling of God in Chriſt Jeſus.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 14.</note> He
plains and ſmoothes his way before him by remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
the impediments and ſlumbling-blocks of
ſcruples, doubts and difficulties, ſtrengthens his
Conſcience, adminiſters cordials and comforts,
and never leaves till he has conducted him ſafe to
the bleſſed end and Reward of all his troubles and
endeavours. The ſinner he warns of the danger of
his ſin, and delivers his own ſoul by endeavouring to
ſave <hi>his.</hi> He lifts up his voice <hi>like a trumpet</hi> and ſpares
not; but ſhews the <hi>people their tranſgreſsion and the houſe
of Jacob their ſin.</hi> He tells them of the danger they
are in, and points to the gaping precipices that are
in their way ready to ſwallow them up into ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:65451:22"/>
deſtruction. He <hi>ſpeaks, exhorts, rebukes with all
authority,</hi> fearleſly he ſets his face and propheſieth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
them.</p>
            <p>And now tell me, does not ſuch a one as this,
that thus in all things approves himſelf <hi>as the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter
of God,</hi> deſerve to be ſtyl'd <hi>chariot and horſemen,</hi> a
great ſupport and defence of the people? Such an
one was <hi>Elijah</hi> here mention'd: and ſuch an one
too was the Holy <hi>Biſhop,</hi> whom I commemorate in
this diſcourſe. You have read the hiſtory of the
former, and ſo know well <hi>what the Scripture ſaith of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lias,</hi>
of his conſtancy in his Religion, and his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
dangers in endeavouring to inſtruct the people
in their duty, and reclaim them from their foul
Apoſtacy, and bring them back to the <hi>Church</hi> and
worſhip of God.</p>
            <p>Nor are you or the world ignorant of your late
<hi>Biſhop's</hi> great <hi>Abilities</hi> and as great <hi>Induſtry</hi> in Teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.
You I ſay of <hi>this</hi> Church eſpecially can <hi>tell of
his wiſdom,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ecclus. 44. 15.</note> and <hi>this</hi> Congregation can <hi>ſhew forth his
praiſe.</hi> You are happy witneſſe how He mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter'd
the gifts that He had received, as a good
<hi>Steward of the manifold grace of God:</hi> You ſaw with
<hi>wonder,</hi> and perhaps, not without <hi>pity,</hi> how unmer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull
He was to <hi>his own body,</hi> that He might be
profitable to <hi>your ſouls,</hi> by his indefatigable labours
in Preaching and in Catechiſing: And not <hi>you</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone
but <hi>all</hi> that ever had the happineſs to be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
his charge, or near the places of his Reſidence,
were, or might have been, not only witneſſes,
but partakers of the benefit of his labours in the
publick. He was never weary of doing Good; and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:65451:22"/>
tho' his body, unable to keep pace with the zeal
and eagerneſs of his mind, languiſh'd and fainted
in the ſervice; yet could He never be perſwaded
in his age and weakneſs to abate any thing of the
toils and hardſhips of his younger and ſtronger
days. He knew God had intruſted him with much,
and therefore was very intent on the great account
He was one day to give of the uſe and improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
of ſo great a treaſure. He had always a
ſteddy eye on <hi>that bleſſed hope and the glorious appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of the great God and our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> A
deep and Religious meditation on this made him
covetous of his time, fearfull and impatient of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting
any opportunity of doing good; for which
He could not but be ſenſible that He was admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably
qualified and prepar'd.</p>
            <p>'Tis true, and He knew it well, that a <hi>Biſhop</hi>
may be able to give a very good account of the
truſt repoſed in him, tho' He be not often in the
<hi>Pulpit</hi> or the <hi>Desk:</hi> He may be <hi>apt to teach</hi> and do
it effectually, tho' He make not many <hi>Sermons,</hi>
in the vulgar uſe and ſignification of the word: If
He makes due inquiſition into the merits and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners
of his <hi>Clergy,</hi> and takes full pains and care to
inſtruct by way of Conference or otherwiſe, to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe,
commend, rebuke, encourage, diſcountenance,
reward, and ceſure as often and as far as occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
ſhall require; He, I ſay, that ſhall conſtantly
and conſcientiouſly diſcharge theſe and ſuch other
acts of Government; as He will not abound with
ſpare time for other purpoſes, ſo will He thereby
moſt certainly benefit and edifie the <hi>Church</hi> much
more then He can do by <hi>Sermons</hi> and ſuch like
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:65451:23"/>
ſet and Solemn Diſcourſes to the people; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
induſtrious He may be and frequent in that
employment.</p>
            <p>But the Great Good man, that I am ſpeaking
of thought He had time and ſtrength enough, for
more then was or could be reaſonably expected
from him. And truly I fear He was much miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
in the judgement He made of the ability of
his <hi>body.</hi> Indeed, nothing could be too much for
his <hi>ſoul:</hi> His mind and memory (admirably
ſtock'd and ſtor'd) plentifully furniſhed out mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
and words, whenever He had occaſion for
them.</p>
            <p>Few men have acquir'd a more general, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,
and comprehenſive knowledge in moſt parts
of Learning than He himſelf had. But in <hi>Theology,</hi>
in the ſtudy of the holy Scriptures and all Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity
uſefull for the explaining and illuſtrating the
Doctrines and Myſteries of our holy Religion, He
was ſo very extraordinarily verſed, that it is hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
poſſible for any to labour therein more fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
and ſuccesfully then did this Prelate. The
foundation of ſo many Excellencies were laid in
his Nature, his Temper and Conſtitution. For (as
I have ſhewn already) God had furniſhed this <hi>cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen
veſſel</hi> with all that was requiſite for the great
improvements and purpoſes, for which He was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended.
His Induſtry from his very Youth was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary
and beyond Example; for the ſupport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of which God had provided him a ſtrong bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,
and a firm health, which laſted him many
years; and, as his Phyſicians and Friends thought,
might have held out much longer could He have
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:65451:23"/>
been perſwaded to have remitted ſomewhat of
his continual pains and ſeverities to himſelf.</p>
            <p>But He was not convinc'd by ſuch their care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
and affectionate remonſtrances for his health.
I wiſh in this one particular He would have been
govern'd more by others then himſelf; for per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps
in this one only could they adviſe him bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.
He found ſuch delight in preparing his
thoughts for the publick, and ſo much pleaſure
after the performance, that He had no leiſure to
obſerve how greatly his <hi>body</hi> had ſuffer'd, and paid
for that ſatisfaction of his <hi>mind.</hi> It was meat and
drink, exerciſe and recreation, life and health to
him to be ſearching the Scriptures, comparing and
pondering on <hi>the lively and holy Oracles of God,</hi> and
then to deliver his happy and well digeſted medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations
to the people: He was <hi>well</hi> when He was
thus employed, as He thought and ſaid; Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as,
indeed, too often this was no more but that
He was <hi>well-pleaſed.</hi> That chearfulneſs and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placency
of mind, which is the preſent natural
reward and conſequent of a conſcientious diſcharge
of duty, that teſtimony and approbation which a
mans own breaſt pays to his ſincerity and worthy
endeavours, this Good <hi>Biſhop</hi> I believe, often inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preted
as an effect of health, and the natural
ſtrength of his own body; or at leaſt, plac'd too
much of it to that account. The weakneſs and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cay,
which He felt in himſelf and could not but
acknowledge, He wholly aſcrib'd to other cauſes,
but would impute nothing of it to his immoderate
pains in Studying and Preaching.</p>
            <p>But, had He been convinc'd that thoſe his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:65451:24"/>
by night and day preſs'd too hard on his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feebled
body and impair'd his health; I queſtion
whether the argument would have prevailed to
have made him ſpare himſelf, as much as his
Friends deſir'd. And for this I have reaſon from
what I have heard him ſay, particularly a day or
two before his laſt ſickneſs, when obſerving his <hi>lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing</hi>
looks, and being in private with him I took
the boldneſs, to inſiſt more vehemently then ever
I had done on this ſubject; For He then with
ſome warmth and earneſtneſs told me that He
would never be perſwaded to indulge his eaſe to
the neglect of any opportunity of doing good,
<hi>&amp; propter vitam vivendi perdere cauſas.</hi> He deſir'd to
live no longer, then when whilſt he might be ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable
to the <hi>Church.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But to return: It is no wonder, that ſo great
natural Endowments carefully cultivated by un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wearied
induſtry and aſſiduous application did mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply
into ſo vaſt an increaſe, and turn at laſt to ſuch
excellent account, as we know they did in this <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop:</hi>
Eſpecially, if we conſider, that He <hi>prayed</hi> as
hard as He <hi>ſtudied.</hi> He well knew that without
God He could do <hi>nothing;</hi> that in order to the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
ſearching the Scriptures and full comprehend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the reveal'd will of God and the Sacred my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries
of our <hi>Holy Faith,</hi> there was need of ſpecial
aſſiſtance from the <hi>Holy Spirit;</hi> and the bleſſing of
him <hi>that teacheth man knowledge,</hi> and conducteth the
pious enquirer <hi>into all Truth;</hi> That otherwiſe it was
<hi>in vain to riſe up early or to ſit up late.</hi> Therefore,
like <hi>Daniel,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 10. 12.</note> He <hi>ſet his heart to underſtand and chaſten'd
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:65451:24"/>
himſelf before his God, and his words were heard,</hi> or,
as the <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 138. 3.</note> He <hi>call'd upon God, and he heard him,
and endued his ſoul with much ſtrength:</hi> Thus was our
Holy <hi>Biſhop</hi> made <hi>wiſe unto ſalvation,</hi> and <hi>profitable</hi> to
his Generation, <hi>for doctrine, for reproof, for correction,
for inſtruction in righteouſneſs:</hi> In a word, as it fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows
in the place to which I allude,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3. 17.</note> A <hi>man of God
perfect and throughly furniſhed unto all good works.</hi>
And <hi>you</hi> have heard and ſeen his wiſdom and his
worth; and not you alone, but many thouſands
of others, all people and places whereever and
with whomſoever He had converſe, can bear true
teſtimony that He <hi>gave</hi> as freely as He had <hi>received,</hi>
and, <hi>like a Scribe inſtructed unto the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi>
was continually ſpending and pouring out his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exhauſtible
Treaſures of Sound Doctrine and Edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying
Knowledge, to the unſpeakable delight and
advantage of thoſe, that came to be inſtructed
by him.</p>
            <p>And they came in great numbers, not of this
Nation only, but from abroad and remoter
Countreys. For that which He did in the <hi>Church</hi>
was the leaſt part of the pains He took, and of his
labouring <hi>in the Word and Doctrine.</hi> But this is no
time and place for a particular account of ſuch
matters. It is well enough known, that his houſe
was rarely without ſome Foreign Viſitant led thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
by the far-ſpread fame of the Renowned <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop:</hi>
Scholars from almoſt all parts of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
world, <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Latines,</hi> flock'd to him;
whom they found, like a true <hi>Apoſtolical Biſhop,
Given to hoſpitality and apt to teach.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 2.</note> His doors and his
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:65451:25"/>
purſe were open to receive and relieve them that
were in want; and his heart and mouth always
ready to inſtruct thoſe that deſired to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed.</p>
            <p>A great part of his time was ſpent in explain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
and juſtifying to ſtrangers and others the
<hi>regular</hi> and <hi>Catholick</hi> conſtitution of the <hi>Church of
England,</hi> and in aſſerting Her <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi>
and whole entire <hi>frame</hi> againſt the oppoſition of
Her Adverſaries, the <hi>Romaniſts,</hi> and all other <hi>Recu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſants</hi>
of various denominations amongſt our ſelves.
And theſe unwearied endeavours of this Holy Man
God has been pleaſed to crown often with good
ſucceſs. Many thereby have been confirmed in the
Communion of the <hi>Church,</hi> with whom Bigots of
<hi>Rome,</hi> or other Zealots of the <hi>Schiſm</hi> had been dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerouſly
tampering. Several quite <hi>ſpirited</hi> away
by ſuch <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> and <hi>Agents</hi> He retriev'd and
brought back again to their <hi>Reaſon</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi>
Foreigners have parted from him not only fill'd
with admiration of his own worth, but alſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
ſatisfied with the excellent Frame and Order of
this <hi>Church,</hi> which had before been ignorantly or
maliciouſly repreſented to them: And the report
which they have accordingly made to their own
people at their return home has rebounded back
and been brought hither again, to the great praiſe and
honour of this <hi>Chriſtian Catholick Church,</hi> ſo happily
eſtabliſh'd in this Land. Theſe (I ſay) are things
well known to many, but not to be by me at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
branch'd out into any of their many great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances,
or expanded to their due advantage. That,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:65451:25"/>
if done according to the dignity of the ſubject and
the great abundance of the matter it affords, would
be a more proper Theme for a <hi>juſt volume</hi> then the
few narrow Pages of a popular <hi>Sermon.</hi> It ſufficeth
me to have ſaid enough on this Head, to ſhew,
that this Prelate was a worthy <hi>Champion</hi> of our
Faith, and an able <hi>Defender</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
very capable of ſuch a compellation as <hi>Eliſha,</hi>
on the account of the like excellencies, gave
to <hi>Elijah: The chariot of Iſrael and the horſemen
thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE <hi>laſt</hi> thing I ſhall inſiſt on, as a reaſon or
juſtification of that <hi>great Title,</hi> is the great good
that is done, and the mighty advantage that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crues
to the Publick from the Lives and Examples of
Good and Holy men, eſpecially thoſe of a <hi>Sacred
Character.</hi> Certain it is, that men are generally con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinc'd
and guided more by their Eyes then Ears.
<hi>Precepts</hi> and <hi>Exhortations</hi> affect the mind but ſlowly
and weakly, whilſt <hi>Actions</hi> and <hi>Examples</hi> move
ſtrongly and with power; ſo that if they be but
advantagiouſly repreſented and duly attended to;
they are <hi>winning</hi> and <hi>perſwaſive,</hi> and have a very
quick and almoſt irreſiſtible influence and efficacy
in ſoliciting the conſent of the will, and prompt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
it to imitation. For virtue <hi>moves practically,</hi> as
<hi>Plutarch</hi> expreſſeth it,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Peric.</note> 
               <hi>moralizing</hi> the beholder, and,
as it were, transforming him into its own likeneſs:
It draws him to imitation neither able nor willing
to reſiſt that <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the ſame <hi>Authour</hi> well
ſtiles the influence of a <hi>Good Example.</hi> Our <hi>Bleſſed
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:65451:26"/>
Saviour</hi> himſelf, tho' anointed to preach the <hi>Goſpel</hi>
by the <hi>Holy Ghoſt,</hi> which He received <hi>without mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi>
and tho' aſſiſted with all the powers of the <hi>God-Head,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Col. 2. 9.</note> which <hi>dwelt bodily in him;</hi> tho' God immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ately
from Heaven, in an audible voice, beſpoke and
prepar'd for him and his <hi>Goſpel</hi> attentive Audience, du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull
Reception, and Univerſal Obedience and
Conformity, as to the words and will of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clar'd
Son of God,<note place="margin">Mat. 17. 5.</note> in whom He was <hi>well-pleaſed;</hi>
And tho' He himſelf taught with <hi>Authority,</hi> and
ſpake as <hi>never man</hi> did,<note place="margin">John 7. 46.</note> according to the frank con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion
of his moſt bloody Enemies; and all
<hi>wondred at the gracious words which proceeded out of his
mouth;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 4. 22.</note> Yet would He not rely on that <hi>voice from
Heaven</hi> or his own <hi>Divine Rhetorick</hi> on Earth, for
the Succeſs of his undertaking, without the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance
of a further Teſtimony and demonſtration
of the Excellency of his Doctrine; and that was
his own <hi>Example.</hi> Therefore He appeals and refers
them to what He <hi>did</hi> as a confirmation of what
He <hi>taught:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 11. 29.</note> 
               <hi>Learn of me,</hi> ſaith He, <hi>for I am meek and
lowly of heart.</hi> And when He had given them a
manifeſt proof of that virtue, ſtooping to ſo low
and mean an Office as the waſhing of his <hi>Diſciples</hi>
feet, He tells them He had given them <hi>an Example
that they ſhould do as He had done.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 13. 15.</note> Nay, this Divine
Preacher, ſent from God and deſcended from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
even in his <hi>farewell Sermon</hi> would not truſt to
the efficacy of thoſe his <hi>laſt words,</hi> without adding
the further and more powerfull argument of his
<hi>Example;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 15. 9, 10.</note> teaching his diſciples <hi>obedience</hi> to himſelf
by his own <hi>obedience</hi> to his father, and <hi>Love</hi> for one
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:65451:26"/>
another by his own <hi>Love</hi> to them. Which argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> not able to find a better, repeats and
urges when He would enforce the ſame duty: <hi>walk
in Love,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epheſ. 5. 2.</note> ſaith He, <hi>as Chriſt alſo hath loved us.</hi> And
S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Peter,</hi> when He was to recommend the moſt
difficult duty, even ſuffering patiently tho' wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully,
and for doing well, found it neceſſary to have
recourſe to <hi>Example</hi> rather than <hi>precept:</hi> And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
ſhould He go for that, but to him, who taught
both by his Life and Death? Even to our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
<hi>Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 20.</note> 
               <hi>who,</hi> ſaith He, <hi>ſuffered for us, leaving us
an Example, that we ſhould follow his ſteps.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this practice of our Saviour is an awfull
Precept to all his followers, but eſpecially to thoſe
whom He ſent <hi>as</hi> his <hi>Father ſent</hi> Him, that they in
like manner, ſhould not be only <hi>Teachers</hi> but <hi>Doers</hi>
of his will; that ſo they may more happily con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm
and propagate their <hi>Doctrine</hi> by their <hi>Practices,</hi>
according to the <hi>Example</hi> of their <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Maſter.</hi>
They that do otherwiſe, whatever they ſay, are
rather <hi>Enemies</hi> than <hi>Friends,</hi> do really more oppoſe
than promote the Cauſe they would ſeem to own:
S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> warneth the <hi>Philippians</hi> to <hi>mark,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3. 17.</note> that is, to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulate
and imitate thoſe that walk'd after ſuch an
<hi>Example</hi> as He had given, but to apprehend of others
as <hi>the enemies of the Croſs of Chriſt.</hi> That great <hi>Apoſtle</hi>
had often denied himſelf innocent and lawfull Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berties,
that He might the more effectually gain
others to the performance of neceſſary duties:
<hi>Not becauſe we have not power</hi> (ſays He to the <hi>Theſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonians)
but to make our ſelves an example unto you to fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low
us.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Theſ. 3. 9.</note> And therefore not to <hi>them</hi> alone did He come
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:65451:27"/>
in more then <hi>Word only</hi> (as he expreſſeth it in his firſt
Epiſtle to them) but others, and on other occaſions,
He frequently provokes to <hi>follow</hi> his <hi>Example,</hi> to <hi>be
followers of him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1. 5.</note> to <hi>be followers together of him;</hi> Uſing
frequently other exhortations of the ſame kind.
Great pains did He take, and much watching and
mortification did He uſe and undergo, <hi>leſt that
by any means,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 27.</note> when He had preach'd to <hi>others,</hi> He <hi>him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
ſhould be a caſt-away.</hi> After ſuch Authorities as
theſe, I need not tell you, that a good Life is the
main Ingredient or the Grand Qualification, which
the <hi>Philoſopher</hi> requires in him that ſets up for a
Teacher; and for this reaſon, becauſe it is not the
<hi>diſcourſe,</hi> but the <hi>opinion</hi> the Auditory has of him that
ſpeaks, that inſtructs and edifies thoſe that hear
him.</p>
            <p>Such, indeed, are the moſt of men; They will
not <hi>lead</hi> but <hi>follow:</hi> You cannot perſwade them e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
to happineſs or Heaven, unleſs you go before
them. It cannot be denied, but that this is their
fault and folly: They are not ſo willfull and
blind in Temporal concerns. But when you ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe
them to quit <hi>preſent</hi> and palpable for <hi>future</hi>
and inviſible advantages and ſatisfactions, they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
encouragement from your own <hi>Example</hi> for ſo
doing. If they obſerve their <hi>Teacher</hi> to do other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
himſelf then He would perſwade them, they
are apt to ſuſpect or pretend that his Doctrine is
impracticable or doubtfull; or that ſome deſign,
forgery, colluſion, ſome diſhoneſt artifice and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice
is in hand and ready to be impos'd upon
them. But our bleſſed Saviour, who himſelf took
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:65451:27"/>
ſuch care to inforce his Doctrine by his example,
forgot not, for all that, to condemn this <hi>madneſs of
the people,</hi> and to cure or prevent it, if poſſible, for
the future; by commanding obedience even to
the <hi>Scribes</hi> and <hi>Phariſees,</hi> as being the appointed pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
Guides and Doctours of the Law: And yet
in the ſame breath, He took care to caution a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt,
the contagion of their bad example:
<hi>The Scribes and the Phariſees ſit in Moſes ſeat.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matt. 23. 2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>All there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
whatſoever they bid you obſerve, that obſerve and do;
but do not you after their works, for they ſay and do not.</hi>
So that it will prove but a bad plea at the laſt
dreadfull <hi>Tribunal,</hi> and a worſe comfort after the
Sentence of condemnation, for any to ſay, that
they would have done better had they ſeen their
<hi>Teacher</hi> do ſo, and that they choſe to go out of the
way for his good company, tho' they had all the
reaſon in the world to believe and He himſelf told
them, that they trod the paths of death, and that
the end of that road was ruine.</p>
            <p>But ſince it is ſo, that the Holy Life of the
<hi>Teacher</hi> is the Life of his <hi>Doctrine,</hi> and that He is
the moſt ſucceſsfull Inſtructour that preaches by his
<hi>good Example;</hi> The great <hi>Prophet</hi> in the Text, and
the great <hi>Prelate,</hi> of whom I ſpeak, do from hence
derive another good plea to the meaning of the
<hi>Phraſe</hi> in the <hi>Text,</hi> and may juſtly be eſteemed to
have been in their generations <hi>chariots and horſemen;</hi>
as that ſignifies <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Defence</hi> unto the Church
and Commonwealth to which they did belong. If
the lips of the Prieſt are to <hi>keep knowledge;</hi> If
the Teachers be, alſo on that account, the <hi>Guar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians</hi>
of our Faith; If ſound Doctrine be the ſhield
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:65451:28"/>
and buckler, the Spiritual Safeguard and Protection
of Religion and conſequently of the people that
profeſs it, and the diſpenſers of it be therefore them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
<hi>Chariots and horſemen;</hi> when the virtue of a <hi>good
Example,</hi> Holineſs of life, upright and unblameable
Converſation ſhall be join'd to their other Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies,
a great <hi>Strength</hi> and <hi>Ornament</hi> will thereby
be added to them; and being now thus compleat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
arm'd, ſafe and invulnerable all over, they will
appear ſtill more redoubted and accompliſh'd <hi>Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pions;</hi>
and ſo further qualified for that honourable
compellation in the <hi>Text.</hi> This is that which helps
to <hi>put to ſhame</hi> the Adverſaries of the <hi>Church,</hi> and as
ſuch it is recommended by an Apoſtle to a Biſhop,
by S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Titus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tit. 2. 7.</note> that to the incorruptneſs of his
Doctrine He ſhould be ſure to add that of his own
Example: <hi>In all things,</hi> (ſaith He) <hi>ſhewing thy ſelf a
pattern of good works, that he that is of the contrary part
may be aſhamed, having no evil thing to ſay of you.</hi> A great
victory eaſily obtain'd: If we run not upon the
Enemies weapons, they will either caſt them away
or turn them upon themſelves.<note place="margin">Verſe 8.</note> 
               <hi>Sound ſpeech that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be condemned,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> there expreſſeth it, and
a ſuitable practice muſt needs either <hi>convince</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found</hi>
the Gainſayers: They will, ſure, be <hi>ſilenc'd</hi> if
they are not <hi>ſatisfi'd,</hi> which laſt, another <hi>Apoſtle</hi> hopes
well from the influence of <hi>a good Example,</hi> which He
enjoyns on this very conſideration;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 3. 1, 2.</note> 
               <hi>That if any obey
not the word, they alſo may without the Word be won over,
whilſt they behold ſuch chaſte converſation coupled with fear.</hi>
There are thoſe that <hi>deſire occaſion,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 12.</note> as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> tells us
in <hi>one</hi> place;<note place="margin">1 Tim. 5. 14.</note> therefore we muſt be ſure to <hi>give the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:65451:28"/>
Adverſary no occaſion to ſpeak reproachfully,</hi> as He admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſheth
in <hi>another.</hi> Very buſie are the Enemies of
<hi>Religion,</hi> always endeavouring to diſcountenance and
undermine the Profeſſours of it. This is the way
to countermine thoſe <hi>deceitfull workers,</hi> to blow up
their Treacherous trains, and expoſe and defeat
their malice. This therefore is very good ſervice
to the <hi>Church,</hi> both as it is a means to <hi>ſecure</hi> what
She hath already gotten, and alſo to <hi>enlarge</hi> Her
conqueſts: And ſurely then ſuch Holy <hi>Warriours</hi>
may with good reaſon be ſtyl'd as we ſee they are,
<hi>The chariots of</hi> our <hi>Iſrael and the horſemen thereof.</hi> They
fear not the utmoſt malice of the world; In the
thickeſt of the Enemy they ſtand invulnerable and
ſecure: Their breaſtplate of <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim,</hi>
ſoundneſs of Doctrine and integrity of Life, is <hi>proof</hi>
and an impenetrable defence againſt all the <hi>fiery darts</hi>
of <hi>Men</hi> or <hi>Devils.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thus was <hi>Elijah</hi> clad, thus armed he contended
earneſtly and ſucceſsfully for the Faith: His con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation
was in Heaven, long before he himſelf
aſcended thither. He liv'd a great pattern of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs
to his Age: His very actions, whilſt his
tongue was ſilent, were ſo many rebukes to that
apoſtatized people; For even by his refuſing to
comply with them He upbraided and rebuked their
abominations. The terrour of Death from the
bloody hand of Tyranny did make him fly, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed;
but could not ſhake his Integrity: This
his conſtancy in the Faith and Worſhip of God
gave as great Teſtimony to the Truth as his Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
did: ſo that <hi>Elijah</hi> taught by his <hi>deeds</hi> as well
as by his <hi>words,</hi> and edifi'd the Church both by his <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi>
and his <hi>Example.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:65451:29"/>
And did not <hi>our Holy Prelate</hi> ſo too? Did not
He ſhew his <hi>Faith</hi> by his <hi>Works? Ye are witneſſes and
God alſo how holily and juſtly and unblameably</hi> He <hi>behav'd
himſelf among you that believe.</hi> For ever bleſſed be our
Gracious God, who, (to the great advantage of his
<hi>Spouſe</hi> the Church and the publick Good) did fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh
this his ſervant with ſuch large meaſures of
his holy Spirit and all Heavenly graces, that He
became a <hi>burning and a ſhining light;</hi> and could not
be more admirable for his extraordinary parts and
vaſt improvements then He was truly venerable for
exemplary Piety and Holineſs of life.</p>
            <p>Had I not already very much tranſgreſſed the
limits of my time, I would boldly inlarge on this
Head, as I eaſily might, ſecure and fearleſs of
ſeeming to any of you to ſay to much, or being
too laviſh in the commendations of the Holy man.
It is a Theme ſcarce capable of Figure or flattery.
His very enemies could not but acknowledge the
uprightneſs of his converſation even when He ſtood
before a <hi>Committee</hi> of them, impeach'd and arraign'd
for his <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Religion.</hi> They could find no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion,
tho' diligently ſought for, againſt him, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept
in that which concern'd <hi>the Law of his God.</hi> They
granted He was a man of Good Life; but that,
they ſaid, made him the more dangerous, for that
ſuch men did all the miſchief: A good teſtimony
from the mouth of the Enemy, of what I was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
ſaying, that nothing confounds them more
then the unblameable Lives of ſuch as profeſs, and
pretend a regard to <hi>Religion,</hi> and obedience to the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:65451:29"/>
               <hi>Church.</hi> When they could not cenſure his <hi>practice,</hi>
they would needs queſtion his <hi>Sermons;</hi> nay, rather
then fail, pick quarrels with his very <hi>Texts;</hi> as they
did with his choice of one that, it ſeems, had too
much <hi>Loyalty</hi> in it for their purpoſe; and that was
ſome of the firſt <hi>Verſes</hi> of the <hi>thirteenth Chapter</hi> to the
<hi>Romans;</hi> to which their <hi>Venerable</hi> Priſoner appoſitely
replied, that He was come prepared to juſtifie his <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
but did not expect to be call'd upon to anſwer
for his <hi>Text:</hi> But it ſeems, in the afternoon, He
had choſen a more <hi>innocent</hi> piece of <hi>Scripture</hi> for the
ſubject of his Diſcourſe; and that was the <hi>Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi>
of the Peacemakers: <hi>Bleſſed are the Peacemakers:</hi>
But when it was alledged by his accuſers, that He
had obſerv'd that <hi>League-makers</hi> were not <hi>Peacemakers,</hi>
this <hi>Text</hi> could no more excuſe his <hi>Sermon</hi> then the
other <hi>Sermon</hi> his <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>This</hi> Paſtour <hi>certainly, if any, was an</hi> Example to
his flock,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5. 3.</note> 
               <hi>in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> Peters Phraſe, <hi>to the</hi> believers, <hi>in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               </hi> Pauls;
<hi>and that in all the particulars there mentiond.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 12.</note> In
word, in converſation, in charity, in ſpirit, in faith, in
purity.</p>
            <p>That He was a faithfull Miniſter of Chriſt, a
conſcientious diſpenſer of the <hi>Word,</hi> and <hi>Steward of
the Myſteries of God,</hi> You have heard already under
another Head, and knew it well before by your
own obſervation and experience.<note place="margin">Acts 11. 24.</note> He never <hi>ſhunn'd to
declare unto you all the Councel of God. For he was a good
man,</hi> (that I may apply the Character of S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Barnabas</hi>
to this <hi>Saint</hi> of ours) <hi>and full of the Holy Ghoſt and of
Faith, and added much people unto the Lord.</hi> Very much
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:65451:30"/>
pains He took to convince and reclaim <hi>Recuſants</hi> of
all ſorts: He invited them to frequent conferences;
<hi>in meekneſs inſtructing thoſe that oppoſed themſelves,</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering
their arguments, reſolving their doubts, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving
their ſcruples, and ſilencing all their Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils
againſt the eſtabliſhed <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of
the Church, and this he did oft-times with moſt
happy ſucceſs: For <hi>the Word of God,</hi> in his mouth,
<hi>was quick and powerfull.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But O how ſincere and great was his joy when
He found God had made him an inſtrument of
bringing back a wandring and a <hi>loſt ſheep!</hi> How
did his humble gratitude iſſue forth of his very eyes,
diſcovering to all, that ſaw and obſerv'd him, his
religious ſoul triumphing in the ſpiritual victory,
and at the ſame time heartily aſcribing it unto
Heaven! But when overgrown and ſtubborn pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judices,
pride, obſtinacy or ſtupidity made his cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable
endeavours ineffectual, 'tis true, the Good
man ſeem'd troubled; He ſigh'd and prayed and
ſent many a pittying and lamenting look after the
hardned and unrelenting <hi>wretch;</hi> but, for all that,
knew how to be content, and, tho' He might ſay,
as the <hi>Prophet</hi> in the perſon of our <hi>Saviour, I have la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour'd
in vain,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 49. 4.</note> 
               <hi>I have ſpent my ſtrength for nought,</hi> yet
withall He could comfortably add that which imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately
follows; <hi>my judgement is with the Lord, and my
work with my God.</hi> His prayers and his pains were
accepted by his great <hi>Maſter</hi> in Heaven, who ſet
him on work, and from thence return'd in ſhowr's
of bleſſings and comfort on his head, and into his
own boſome. But when this was done, when to
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:65451:30"/>
the Laws, and the weighty conſiderations of publick
ſafety and quiet, common utility and general ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
of the miſchievous effects of the <hi>ſeparation</hi>
(all which pleaded ſtrongly on his ſide) I ſay, when
to theſe He had added his own publick and private
endeavours to remove all, if there were any real
conſcientious ſcruples and difficulties in the caſe;
He was far from thinking it an <hi>Uſurpation upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences,</hi>
to remit refractory perſons to the <hi>Civil</hi> pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
to be proceeded againſt by <hi>legal proſecutions,</hi> the
likelieſt means then remaining, not only to prevent
the increaſe of their numbers, but to bring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves
to <hi>Church,</hi> and thereby give them opportunity
to hear and hearken to further inſtructions, more
attentively and effectually then otherwiſe they would
have done.</p>
            <p>But I muſt haſten to an end. As for his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon
converſe it was pleaſant, affable and courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous,
and yet ſtill grave and highly becoming his
<hi>Sacred Character.</hi> That doubtfulneſs and fear which
his Venerable <hi>Preſence,</hi> his high <hi>Station</hi> and Quality,
together with his great and juſt <hi>Renown</hi> did frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
produce in ſtrangers at their firſt approach, was
by the <hi>eaſineſs</hi> of the <hi>acceſs</hi> they met with, by his
<hi>humble</hi> and courteous deportment, and all-obliging
<hi>affability</hi> and condeſcenſion ſoon converted into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect
<hi>Delight</hi> and <hi>Love. So ſweet and heavenly a tempera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
there was in him of Greatneſs and Goodneſs, of Meek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
and Majeſty, of Gravity and Courteſie, of every thing,
indeed, that is amiable and Reverend; that it was impoſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to know him well and not to Honour and Delight in him.</hi>
Something like this has perhaps been fancied in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:65451:31"/>
but the <hi>whole Character</hi> was hardly ever more tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
applied to any then to this <hi>Biſhop.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If ever that which we call <hi>Good nature</hi> did <hi>abound</hi>
in any man, it did in him; but ſo refin'd, beautified
and ſet off by <hi>Religion,</hi> that ſurely it ſcarce ever
ſhin'd with more luſtre and lovelineſs in any then
in our <hi>Prelate.</hi> Even they that went from him diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>appointed
of their hopes (which none did that
had not <hi>unreaſonably</hi> entertain'd them) could never
find in their hearts to be diſpleas'd with him: So
much reaſon did He always give for his denial,
ſuch kind pains would He take to ſatisfie the <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioner,</hi>
tho' He could not grant his <hi>requeſt,</hi> ſo loath
was He to diſmiſs him from his preſence till He
had ſcatter'd all ſigns of diſcontent (if any did a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe)
from his countenance, That it was evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
the Good <hi>Prelate</hi> was more troubled that He
could not <hi>give,</hi> then the other that he did not
<hi>receive.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſubject of his diſcourſe, as far as <hi>Decenty</hi>
and <hi>Company</hi> would allow, was generally about mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
of <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Learning.</hi> It was his great buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
to be <hi>doing or receiving</hi> good; conſidering that
ſo employed He was moſt acceptable to that <hi>One</hi>
Maſter, whoſe ſervice He had choſen. He gladly
put all that came near him upon diſcourſes of
things of which they were moſt likely and able to
give the beſt account, which was the moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bable
way to oblige them and benefit himſelf:
Tho', for the moſt part, Thoſe, who He ſeem'd
to hear and confer with for his own inſtruction,
He really <hi>taught</hi> and ſent away better informed in
the very things wherein they thought themſelves
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:65451:31"/>
to excell. Never was that <hi>Apoſtolical</hi> qualification
of a <hi>Biſhop's</hi> being <hi>apt to teach</hi> more eminently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
then in him; Whether we conſider the word
as it ſignifies <hi>ability,</hi> or elſe <hi>inclination</hi> to inſtruct
and edifie others. Of the firſt I have diſcourſed
already: The other is as famouſly known as
that.</p>
            <p>Some greatly Learned men have been noted to
be very reſerv'd in converſation, as if they envy'd
or grudg'd the world, or, at leaſt, their company,
the riches of their diſcourſe; That they could ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom
be perſwaded to deliver their judgements, or
that, when they did, it was in ſo dark and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex't
a manner that it edified but little: Much
further were they from freely giving the reaſons
of their opinion, and ſubmitting them to the debate
and examination of others.</p>
            <p>But it was quite otherwiſe with the <hi>Biſhop:</hi> He
was as an open fountain, free, plentifull and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municative:
Always asking and anſwering que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions
in all parts of Learning, but eſpecially ſuch
as might conduce to the clearing of <hi>obſcure</hi> places of
<hi>Scripture,</hi> or the confirming ſome <hi>Doctrine</hi> or Article
of Faith, or ſome other <hi>Theological Verity.</hi> For that
was the end of all his Studies; To this. He directed
all his endeavours; and well underſtood how to
keep and uſe other <hi>Arts</hi> and <hi>Soiences</hi> in due ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordination
and ſubſerviency to the ſtudy of <hi>Divine</hi>
matters, to the knowledge of God and his own
duty; for which He knew He was born, and which
He deſir'd and valued above all other acquiſitions in
the world. This eager bent of his <hi>heart</hi> fram'd and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon'd
all his <hi>converſation,</hi> giving it the tincture of his
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:65451:32"/>
inward thoughts; ſo that it plainly appear'd, out of
what <hi>abundance</hi> it was that his mouth ſpake.</p>
            <p>In my <hi>Text</hi> it is obſerv'd that the <hi>chariot and horſes
of fire</hi> appear'd whilſt the two <hi>Prophets</hi> walk'd and
talk'd together. Some will be gueſſing at the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars
of their diſcourſe. But, whether we con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
the <hi>men,</hi> the <hi>occaſion,</hi> or that part of the <hi>conference</hi>
which is <hi>recorded,</hi> we have reaſon to conclude that
it was all holy and good, relating either to Gods
honour on Earth, or the now approaching felicity
of <hi>Elijah</hi> in a better place. But ſure I am, that our
Holy <hi>Prelate</hi> was almoſt conſtantly <hi>ſpeaking of the
things pertaining to the Kingdom of God:</hi> It was
the language of his <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Health,</hi> of his hail
and <hi>Youthfull</hi> days, as well as of his <hi>Old Age</hi> and
the bed of ſickneſs and death. And truly, in
all other <hi>Religious</hi> reſpects, as well as this, his
Death was but like his Life, his latter end ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly
conformable to his more early days. I
could not obſerve of him (as <hi>Pliny</hi> from his friend,<note place="margin">Nuper me cujuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam amici lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guor admonuit optimos eſſe nos dum infirmi ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus. <hi>Plin. Ep. 26. lib.</hi> 7.</note>
did of all men) that He was beſt in ſickneſs. A
pious diſpoſition of mind expreſs'd by a conſtant
uniform Tenour of Holy and Devout Practice
had been very viſible through the whole courſe
of his Life, and it accompanied him to the
laſt. He had no new promiſes and profeſſions
of Reformation to make;<note place="margin">Tales eſſe ſani perſeveremus quales nos fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turos profitemur infirmi: <hi>ibid.</hi>
               </note> as the ſame <hi>Authour</hi>
in that ſame <hi>Epiſtle</hi> intimates, and common ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience
ſhews to be the cuſtom of men on the
bed of ſickneſs: He had <hi>liv'd</hi> ſo as He would
be contented to <hi>die;</hi> and all the uſual or ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
buſineſs of the ſick bed, Repentance,
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:65451:32"/>
Mortification and Holy Vows had been the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py
Work of his ſtrongeſt and healthfull days.
By a Religious uſe of thoſe <hi>frequent Communions,</hi>
which, to his everlaſting Praiſe, this Holy Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop
eſtabliſh'd or practis'd <hi>weekly</hi> in all places
where He liv'd, and which were ſubject to his
Juriſdiction, He had nouriſh'd and encreas'd in
his Boſome a watchfull and wary diſpoſition of
mind, that kept him perpetually <hi>upon his Guard;</hi>
his Saviours Death and his own being always
ſo before his eyes, that He could not eaſily
be ſurpriz'd by the moſt haſty ſummons to leave
the world. Indeed his whole Life was, in a
manner, a perpetual Faſt and Mortification,
and ſo a good preparation for Death. Plenty
of all things flowed round about him, but for
the uſe of others rather then himſelf. His ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy
and his buſineſs was his meat and drink;
for of any other He had as little regard and
made as little uſe, as was well poſſible to fleſh
and blood. He that had writ ſo <hi>irrefragably</hi> for
the <hi>Faſts</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> kept them as rigidly
himſelf. But that ſuffic'd him not: He oblig'd
himſelf to ſo many others, that they who knew
not what Excellent Uſe his <hi>mind</hi> made of thoſe
hours of Abſtinence might ſuſpect that ſo much
ſeverity to his <hi>body,</hi> inclin'd ſomewhat towards
a fault.</p>
            <p>I am very ſenſible how my Subject grows
upon my hands, which makes me grow bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denſome
to your patience. Much matter and
many thoughts croud in upon me; which I muſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:65451:33"/>
refuſe, remembring where and what I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout;
that it is a <hi>Sermon</hi> and not an <hi>Hiſtory</hi> that
I have in hand. However, methinks, I ſhould
not omit one thing which was moſt remarkable
in the <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and is very proper to be men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion'd
in a <hi>Pulpit;</hi> and that is his <hi>Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi>
which is another of thoſe Virtues where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> would have a <hi>Biſhop</hi> be <hi>Exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Take this in its full latitude, of love both
to God and man, it was as eminent in your
late <hi>Prelate</hi> as any other of thoſe many <hi>Chriſtian
Graces,</hi> wherewith God had adorn'd and bleſs'd
that Excellent man. As it relates to the doing
kind and <hi>charitable</hi> Offices, the good <hi>Biſhop</hi> did ſo
tranſcend in it, that He ſeem'd nothing more
then a provident and faithfull <hi>Steward</hi> for the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
and the poor. But I know not how to
apply my ſelf to this particular Head, where to
begin or where to end. In the concluſion of a long
diſcourſe and your tired patience, to undertake
a new Theme of ſo vaſt an extent, that it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be treated and diſplayed, as it ought in as
much time as I have already ſpent in all the
other particulars, muſt needs be to the injury
either of the <hi>Subject</hi> or the <hi>Auditory.</hi> I will leave
it therefore to ſpeak it ſelf. Let the <hi>Scholars</hi> He
has ſupported in the <hi>Univerſity</hi> of <hi>Cambridge;</hi> His
ſeveral large <hi>Indowments</hi> and bountifull Benefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions
in that place; Let the crouds of poor fed
daily at his <hi>door,</hi> and from his <hi>Table,</hi> the Wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow,
the Fatherleſs and the Stranger, indigent
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:65451:33"/>
foreigners, diſtreſſed Travellers, and the other
various objects of <hi>Charity publickly fed, cloath'd</hi> and
<hi>reliev'd,</hi> or <hi>privately ſupplied</hi> by him with a <hi>plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full</hi>
hand; Let theſe, I ſay, ſince they <hi>are many,</hi>
ſpeak firſt: Let them all, according to their
Age and Abilities, in their ſeveral Capacities
and Languages, riſe up and bleſs and publiſh
the Praiſes of him, whom living they experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enc'd
a carefull <hi>Father,</hi> a liberal <hi>Patron,</hi> and mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nificent
<hi>Benefactour.</hi> Then there will be nothing
left for me to tell you; but that as He <hi>liv'd</hi>
ſo He <hi>dy'd:</hi> What He had not <hi>charitally</hi> ſpent by
retail before; He did <hi>ſo</hi> diſpoſe of all together
and in the lump, by his <hi>laſt Will</hi> and <hi>Teſtament,</hi>
in which He has taken care that all the remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
part of his Eſtate ſhall be laid out for the
augmentation of poor Vicaridges; A Charity as <hi>pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent</hi>
and <hi>pious</hi> in the <hi>kind</hi> as <hi>bountifull</hi> in the <hi>meaſure</hi>
of it.</p>
            <p>Thus Liv'd; and thus Dyed this Great and
Holy <hi>Biſhop</hi> in the <hi>Seventy firſt</hi> year of his Life,
a Good Old Age as He had made it to himſelf
and others, by having endeavour'd and done ſo
much good in it; but not without hard travail,
laſſitude and toyl which He had brought and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd
upon himſelf, by conſidering more the
<hi>willingneſs</hi> of the <hi>Spirit</hi> then the <hi>wearineſs</hi> of the <hi>Fleſh,</hi>
and ſtriving to live <hi>too faſt</hi> in the beſt ſence; that
is, to be more uſefull and ſerviceable then his
Health and Strength (tho' He had a great ſhare
of both) was able to endure.</p>
            <p>Whilſt God afforded him the uſe of his ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes
and his tongue, He employed them (as He
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:65451:34"/>
was wont) in Prayers and Praiſes and other
Diſcourſes that tended moſt to his own comfort,
and to the Edification of the ſtanders by. Whilſt
I waited on him, which I thank God I had
the Happineſs to do, before his ſickneſs had
too much ruffled or diſcompos'd his thoughts,
He was frequently putting up ardent Prayers
for the Wellfare and Proſperity of the <hi>Church:</hi> He
could not forget to recommend that to the
care of Heaven with ſome of his laſt breath,
which had ever been much dearer to him then
his own Life, which He had ſpent in the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice
of it, with no leſs benefit to the <hi>Church,</hi>
then Honour and Satisfaction to Himſelf: When
ever the fiercer aſſaults of his Feavour began to
remit, and afford him ſome intervall of eaſe,
He preſently return'd to the <hi>Beloved Subject;</hi> and
the next words we heard were concerning the
<hi>Church.</hi> His ſereneſt thoughts were ſpent on this,
and He ſeemed unſenſible of pain, and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get
that He was ſick, whilſt He was Praying
for the Health of the <hi>Spouſe of Chriſt.</hi> Once par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly,
in my hearing, did He make a large
and ſolemn declaration of his devout thanks,
<q>which, ſaid He, I render to Almighty God
with all the powers of my mind, and from the
depth of my ſoul for his moſt wonderfull
Mercy to mankind in his Eternal Son our
Lord and Saviour <hi>Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </q> Then, after
ſome more words to the ſame effect, He re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated
that Verſe of the thirty firſt <hi>Pſalm. Bleſſed
be the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 31. 21.</note> 
               <hi>for he hath ſhewed me his mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vellous
kindneſs in a ſtrong City;</hi> the Holy Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:65451:34"/>
Church, raiſing his voice very ſtrongly
when He ſo interpreted and applied the <hi>Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt's
Phraſe.</hi> Then again He proceeded to ſpeak
of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> which He did with ſo
much Honour, Reverence and Affection, that
not <hi>my</hi> words nor any <hi>other</hi> but his own are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
to expreſs it. Often have I heard him <hi>preach</hi>
and often <hi>diſpute,</hi> and ſtill oftner <hi>Diſcourſe</hi> private<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
in the Juſtification and Honour of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi>
as it was contriv'd and manag'd and now
ſtands by Law Eſtabliſh'd in theſe Kingdoms:
And this He always did with a fervency and
zeal worthy of the Excellent and Deſerving Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject:
But theſe his dying expreſſions, methoughts,
outdid all that ever He had us'd before. In
<hi>few words</hi> (which I dare not pretend to repeat)
He fully expreſs'd his admiration of the <hi>Beauty</hi>
and <hi>Soundneſs</hi> of the conſtitution of the <hi>Church of
England;</hi> and applauded the unvaluable <hi>Happineſs</hi>
of the Nation in it, and bleſſed the <hi>goodneſs</hi> of
God for it, and own'd it for the unſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able
<hi>Comfort</hi> of his Soul, and his <hi>Glory</hi> that
He had liv'd, and now ſhould die, a mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
of it.</p>
            <p>Thus heartily and highly was this <hi>Church</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteemed
and honoured by this moſt <hi>Learned</hi> and
<hi>Holy</hi> Man: Such were his <hi>laſt,</hi> his <hi>dying</hi> thoughts
and expreſſions concerning it; and agreeable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto
had been the Profeſſion and Practice of
his whole Life. As He liv'd ſo He dyed a
<hi>Zealous aſſertour</hi> of our <hi>Reformation.</hi> For this He
had appear'd and acted ſeveral ways, ſo often
and ſo ſucceſsfully, that He was long ſince be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:65451:35"/>
come very formidable to our Adverſaries in the
<hi>Church of Rome;</hi> who at length, found it expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient
to caution their <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> againſt contend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
with <hi>Him.</hi> None underſtood the true ſtate
and full compaſs of the Controverſie between
<hi>the two Churches</hi> better then himſelf, or could
with more Evidence and Conviction make out
the Warrantableneſs and Regularity of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh
Reformation,</hi> the <hi>Canonical proceedings</hi> in it,
the <hi>Excellent Pattern</hi> propos'd and imitated by
it, the moſt <hi>Apoſtolick</hi> and truly <hi>Catholick Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution</hi>
that did ariſe from it, and all the happy
<hi>Advantages</hi> that were obtained by that bleſſed
undertaking; to which we owe, as our <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi>
with much thankfullneſs and comfort was
wont to acknowledge and avouch, <hi>that, at this day,
by a ſingular felicity, we enjoy the envied Communion
of a Church the moſt exactly conformable to the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive
and pureſt of any other Chriſtian Society upon
Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>On the other ſide, He knew as well how
moſt effectually to expoſe the <hi>Uncatholick</hi> impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions
and <hi>Anathema's</hi> of the <hi>Romiſh Church,</hi>
and to ſhew plainly how unlike She is become
to Her <hi>Firſt Self,</hi> how prodigiouſly <hi>deform'd</hi> and
<hi>overgrown</hi> with monſtrous <hi>Innovations</hi> in <hi>Doctrine</hi>
and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> how <hi>unchriſtian</hi> in Her <hi>Uſurpation,</hi> and
in Her <hi>Tyranny</hi> inſupportable: To explain and
maintain ſuch <hi>Truths</hi> as theſe was the buſineſs of
the <hi>Biſhop's</hi> ſtudy, ſpent a great deal of his Time, and
was ſome part of his daily work, even to the laſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:65451:35"/>
But all this could not ſecure the Good Man
from the malicious? and impudent Calumnies
and Railing of ſuch as were Enemies to <hi>Him,</hi>
becauſe they were ſo to <hi>Religion</hi> and the <hi>Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick.</hi>
The moſt Heavenly <hi>Innocence</hi> is not <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dote</hi>
ſufficient againſt the <hi>venome</hi> of the Tongue;
that is, it cannot prevent the malignant aſſaults
of a <hi>Serpentine</hi> brood of people, that will be vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting
out poiſon, tho' they cannot hurt: Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice
will be <hi>gnawing</hi> at the moſt entire and ſolid
Virtue; which, tho' it be <hi>impenetrable</hi> armour,
and a <hi>ſure</hi> defence, yet is it ſtill the <hi>Envy</hi> and
<hi>Aime</hi> of thoſe men,<note place="margin">Pſal. 57. 4.</note> 
               <hi>whoſe teeth are ſpears and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows,
and their Tongue a ſharp ſword.</hi> All the
<hi>Zealous</hi> endeavours, I ſay, of our Learned <hi>Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop</hi>
againſt <hi>the Romaniſts,</hi> and his many Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctories
and Succeſſes in that Cauſe, could not
hinder, (as, doubtleſs, you remember, and not
without much indignation, at the very thought
of it) but that the <hi>Faction</hi> voted and reported
this <hi>unwearied Champion</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Church</hi> a
very <hi>Papiſt.</hi> But it was at a time, indeed, when
it ſeemed very behoofull for <hi>their</hi> purpoſes, that
the beſt <hi>Subjects</hi> and the beſt <hi>Churchmen</hi> ſhould
be ſo reputed: And, accordingly, it was in
ſuch good company that the <hi>Biſhop</hi> ſuffer'd: For
almoſt all the <hi>Loyal Nobility, Clergy</hi> and <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try</hi>
fell under the ſame injurious imputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But all that popular Madneſs and Malice did
but ſerve to exerciſe and Illuſtrate new <hi>Graces</hi>
in our Holy <hi>Prelate,</hi> and bring ſtill further into
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:65451:36"/>
the light the more hidden and undiſcover'd Beauties
of his ſoul. By this means it did appear how
ſmoothly and evenly He could go through or
lie under <hi>good</hi> and <hi>evil report,</hi> and how perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
He had learn'd from the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> both <hi>to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
and ſuffer reproach.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4. 10.</note> All their tumult and
noiſe was not able to diſcompoſe the ſweet
calmneſs and ſerenity of his mind, which the
inward teſtimony and applauſe of his own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
had made ſure and perpetual to him.
The ſlanders and clamours of people <hi>againſt him</hi>
could not riſe higher and louder then his Wiſhes
and Prayers <hi>for them.</hi> He <hi>bleſs'd</hi> as faſt as they
could <hi>curſe:</hi> And when the rage of the Rabble
began to ſwell high, and at laſt became threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
and dangerous, yet was He not then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd
for any intereſt of his own; ſo much
were his thoughts poſſeſs'd with the generous
apprehenſions He had for thoſe miſerable peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple
themſelves, and the fatal Miſchiefs which
their unbridled Fury might bring upon the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment</hi>
and the <hi>Publick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I have done; The time will not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit
of any more: I muſt leave both the Death-bed
and the Grave of this Great Man: And
I am e'ne glad that I am to procede no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.
You could bear, it ſeems with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lixneſs
of my Diſcourſe, whilſt I was ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
of his <hi>Life,</hi> but may not perhaps, ſo well
endure the galling of your Memories with ſad
Reflexions upon his <hi>Death. Eliſha</hi> himſelf could
not look on with Patience when <hi>Elijah</hi> was <hi>parted</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:65451:36"/>
from him, tho? He ſaw him aſcending into
Heaven: Nor can you, I dare ſay, reflect
upon the laſt <hi>Hours</hi> of your late <hi>Biſhop's Life,</hi> tho'
they were the laſt of his <hi>labours</hi> too, without
troubled and ſorrowfull hearts: For it is to <hi>your</hi>
almoſt irreparable <hi>Loſs,</hi> tho' to his unſpeakable
<hi>Advantage</hi> that He was taken from you. To
conclude therefore.</p>
            <p>Let Virtue have its <hi>perfect work;</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Plut. Peric.</note> that effect,
I mean, upon you, which the <hi>Moraliſt</hi> tells us
is natural unto it; that is to diſpoſe men not
only to Praiſe or <hi>Admire</hi> things well done, but
likewiſe to <hi>imitate</hi> the doers of them. I dare
ſay, this Holy <hi>Biſhops</hi> memory is precious to
you, and you would do it Honour: Then uſe
your beſt endeavours to practice his Doctrine
and imitate his Virtues: Recollect ſome, at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaſt,
of the many Divine Precepts and Rules
He has often, with ſo much Religious vehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mence,
deliver'd, explain'd and preſs'd upon
you from this place; and make conſcience to
put in practice thoſe his Pious Admonitions,
which you know the Holy <hi>Biſhop</hi> recommended
both by <hi>Word</hi> and <hi>Deed.</hi> This, as it will beſt
expreſs your eſteem of him, by teſtifying your
value of his Advice and your confidence in his
<hi>Abilities</hi> and <hi>Integrity;</hi> So will it likewiſe ſpeak
your care and kindneſs for your ſelves. Such
practice made your <hi>Biſhop Famous</hi> and <hi>Honourable</hi>
here, and has rais'd him, without doubt, to
a very <hi>high degree</hi> of <hi>Glory</hi> in another world.
The ſame means will produce the ſame happy
effects for you that they did for him: Imitate,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:65451:37"/>
I ſay, his Excellencies all of you, in your ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral
Stations, as far as they are imitable by
you, and perſevere in well doing; And then
you will not fail to be made partakers of thoſe
ineſtimable Rewards of <hi>Glory</hi> and <hi>Immortality,</hi>
which God hath laid up for them who <hi>dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
ſeek him;</hi> which that we may all endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour
faithfully and conſtantly, God of his infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite
mercy grant; <hi>to whom be glory and honour and
praiſe now and for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
